<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethan Reed</title>
    <description>Personal blog of Ethan Reed, PhD Candidate in English Literature at the University of Virginia.
</description>
    <link>http://reedeth.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://reedeth.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 15:29:40 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 15:29:40 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;Tom&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &#39;Hi, Tom&#39; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 13:53:27 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/jekyll/update/2016/01/19/welcome-to-jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/jekyll/update/2016/01/19/welcome-to-jekyll.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visualization #2 of Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So with a significant amount of help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to get &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062045&quot;&gt;this force-directed graph&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3js.org&lt;/a&gt; up and running with my data set from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;“Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period”&lt;/a&gt;. This force-directed graph is one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bost.ocks.org/mike/&quot;&gt;Mike Bostock’s many graphs and visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. I used what he had up on d3, replaced his data set with mine, then with a ton of help from Eric figured out how to get it to read and represent my .csv file even though the original was primed to read a .json data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see below are a series of force-directed graphs. &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/james-p-ascher/&quot;&gt;James&lt;/a&gt; recently made a similar representation of his cloud data using one such graph, which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/cloud-data-present/i&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this post, I produced one force-directed graph for each day and a sprawling, magnificent mess at the end that combines all seven days. In these graphs, each node (or point) represents a “thing” that I used. If you hover over the node with your mouse you can see which thing it represents. Every edge or connecting line represents a connection between those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this representation, a connection between Thing A and Thing B means that Thing A was used right after or right before Thing B in my linear sequence of use as recorded in the data. This means that many aspects of my data were collapsed  in this particular representation. For example: if a thing was used more once in my original data, this does not appear on these graphs. The order of use is also completely gone. So a significant amount of context has been sheared off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we’re left with, however, is something new, and I hope worthwhile on it’s own. It is very different, and perhaps more interesting as a visualization of data, than  &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;my first “visualization”&lt;/a&gt; of this same dataset. Here you can start to see the way different days take different physical shapes in this graph, depending on the kinds of things use and their “connectedness” to other things in their network. For example, Thursday’s things (a day in which I took &lt;a href=&quot;http://nycshuttle.com/&quot;&gt;a bus&lt;/a&gt; from Charlottesville to NYC) live in big billowing petals of connection that loop out on their own for extended series of edges. On the other hand, Sunday, during which I took the same bus &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; to Charlottesville from NYC, lives in much tighter, centralized clusters with fewer strands of relative un-connectedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, more on what all this might mean later. Right now I’m still just practicing getting these things operational and embedded in a post on our site (in this case using &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Gist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/&quot;&gt;bl.ocks.org&lt;/a&gt;). I plan on writing a post reflecting on this whole process and synthesizing a bit, and maybe even one more visualization. We’ll see. Until then: the graphs themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday, 11.2.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/8259c3984ad826227c6d/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, 11.3.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/bf87d62d2c52e815a9ae/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, 11.4.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/18dedb74e52b69a8fbed/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday, 11.5.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/7f8e0cb2446004ffe39c/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, 11.6.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/577082f32ea974c76958/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 11.7.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/97800a0d03021f0dc65a/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday, 11.8.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/d3b68c10128d46fb6f28/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All seven days combined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/57868ff574651558813a/&quot; width=&quot;2100px&quot; height=&quot;1650px&quot; /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 15:39:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/11/20/visualization-2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/11/20/visualization-2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visualization #1 of Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve tried a few different &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery&quot;&gt;visualization examples&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;the d3 site&lt;/a&gt;. They are amazing. The one I used here is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasondavies.com/parallel-sets/&quot;&gt;“Parallel Sets”&lt;/a&gt; and made by Jason Davies. You can find here &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets&quot;&gt;the github page that I took this code from originally&lt;/a&gt;, with his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets/blob/master/LICENSE&quot;&gt;license here&lt;/a&gt;. With a LOT of &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/wayne-graham/&quot;&gt;Wayne’s&lt;/a&gt; help I was able to get this thing operable with my data set, which can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/every&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but is really just a .csv file of my previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;“Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period”&lt;/a&gt;. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/28701d282419c7f37a25/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, in my capable hands Davies’ once beautiful graph has been promptly turned into an incomprehensible - though still, amazingly, interactive - scribble. As a visualization of data, it’s pretty close to nonsensical. This doesn’t come as a surprise to me, as I more or less just tried to crowbar my set of data into Davies’ code/setup until something came up that looked anything like his original graph. Which is does! Sort of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at Davies’ original visualization, it’s of survivors of the Titanic according to four dimensions: survived/perished, female/male, child/adult, second-class/first-class/third-class/crew. On the page he calls it “a visualization technique for multidimensional categorical data.” I don’t think I would describe, exactly, what I have here as “multidimensional categorical data.” But the graph keeps trying to read it as such. So when you hover over certain lines, it’s trying to give you a kind of multidimensional look at a given object, though because my .csv file is probably sloppy and things haven’t been connected right, what it ends up giving is … totally unclear. Some sort of causality is at work, but only my laptop really knows what’s going on (or &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, I actually find what it comes up with kind of poetic. When you mouse over a line (which is almost impossible for a lot of the lines because it’s all so tightly nested) the graph keeps trying to produce a wandering, garbled, yet charming narrative of objects. Maybe what gets me is that there’s a logic at work here, but only the site and my computer can understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; things are happening, things &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; happening - I get the results of this logic in the visualization, pseudo-stories like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;spoons -&amp;gt; mouse pad -&amp;gt; backpack -&amp;gt; chair -&amp;gt; yogurt -&amp;gt; metro card&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This combination that doesn’t show up in my writing at all, but when it comes out of the graph on its own it has a kind of personality to it (yogurt on the subway - a spoon-based mousepad?). Here’s a short, punchy, no-nonsense set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;iPhone -&amp;gt; stairs -&amp;gt; toothpaste&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my personal favorite:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whoever made this last one must have been so sleepy. It looks like something I would produce at the end of the day, mind drifting elsewhere, drowsy, hungry. Sheets, sheets, sheets!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention there’s this whole twilight zone of gray hollow graph on the right, representative of empty cells on my .csv file (some days had more “things used” than others) … &lt;a href=&quot;http://vignette1.wikia.nocookie.net/powerlisting/images/6/6d/Supermassive_black_hole.jpeg/revision/latest?cb=20121206160459&quot;&gt;maybe don’t go over there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of even trying to get this working, I think I want to try using another example from d3 just for the practice of it. Next is probably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mbostock.github.io/d3/talk/20111116/bundle.html&quot;&gt;hierarchical edge bundling example&lt;/a&gt;. Until then!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 14:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/21: When Things Break</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The third of my four installments (here’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;) of Inktober. And oh boy, get ready for some strange-looking sketches in this one. I tried to use a new kind of pen that has two tips and can make way thicker marks, which has resulted in many many failed drawings and a few semi-successful ones. I present to you the semi-successful ones. (For those interested in drawing implements, I’ve been using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sakuraofamerica.com/pen-archival&quot;&gt;0.35mm Pigma Micron&lt;/a&gt; but this time tried out a &lt;a href=&quot;http://tombowusa.com/dual-brush-pen-602.html&quot;&gt;Tombow Dual Brush Pen, N15 black&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems I had with my tools this week, believe it or not, fits thematically with what I’ve been trying to draw: when things break. Or when things (tools) don’t work the way you want them to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with time? Let’s look at the first picture I’m sharing, a drawing of one of my shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.23samba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right samba&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably can’t tell from what I drew here, but this shoe is thrashed on the inside. The back heel has completely torn through the cloth and this bluish plastic is exposed. There’s also a split starting on the outer-toe area through the leather but I couldn’t really draw it that well. On a side note, looking so closely at my shoe for so long reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Ug3ArDMHLnQC&amp;amp;pg=PA540&amp;amp;lpg=PA540&amp;amp;dq=delillo+underworld+shoe+name+the+parts&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=fWnNKYyQUi&amp;amp;sig=KI5UxZA50WbPPs_DtATUDEeNygE&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAmoVChMI8N3n85_UyAIVRHY-Ch08OAK9#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=delillo%20underworld%20shoe%20name%20the%20parts&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;this scene from Don DeLillo’s &lt;em&gt;Underworld&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - from “Sometimes I think…” to the bottom of p. 543 - in which a boy is asked to name as many parts of a shoe as possible. I, in particular, had problems with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shoeguide.org/shoe_anatomy/&quot;&gt;the vamp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Point being, the shoe is beat, from toe cap to insole. It’s spent. Both of my shoes are. I’ve worn these &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adidas.com/us/samba-classic-shoes/034563.html&quot;&gt;sambas&lt;/a&gt;  practically every day since I bought them and often play soccer in them. I will have to buy a new pair very soon. What’s interesting is the way in which I learn that they need to be replaced: I need to buy a new pair because the shoe, as a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt;, has “stopped working.” It’s a trigger of some kind that produces an almost automatic response: thing you need breaks? Time to get a new one! Normally, I don’t think about my shoes at all. They’re comfortable and easy to walk in, so they’re just kind of there - they’re “present at hand” (or “at foot”! Ha!). I know they exist, but I’m no more aware of them than I am of my feet, legs, or hips while walking around. That is, until something goes wrong - the felt wears out and chafes my heel; I start to get blisters; the bottom cushioning wears through; the shoe splits at a side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Heidegger, when a piece of equipment breaks or malfunctions &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#ModEnc&quot;&gt;it acquires a new kind of visibility&lt;/a&gt;, as though it were semi-transparent before while being used. (If you’re wondering what Heidegger is doing here or want more context, check out my &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; posts). Most importantly, this new visibility changes how and what the thing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; - the implication being that situational contexts actually change &lt;em&gt;what things are&lt;/em&gt; for us (Dasein) in the world. So when my shoe ‘breaks,’ it changes how it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in the everyday-ness of my world. It stops being a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polyvore.com/cgi/img-thing?.out=jpg&amp;amp;size=l&amp;amp;tid=71957156&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoe&lt;/em&gt; shoe&lt;/a&gt; and starts being a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.celia-pardini.fr/_/rsrc/1316020452111/my-destroyed-shoes/destroyShoes3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;trash&lt;/em&gt; shoe&lt;/a&gt;. Its time is up. In his 1935 essay &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger-aesthetics/#HeiForArtIntThrPilHeiUndArt&quot;&gt;“The Origin of the Work of Art,”&lt;/a&gt; Heidegger himself actually looks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://harpers.org/wp-content/uploads/van-gogh-a-pair-of-shoes.jpg&quot;&gt;a famous pair of shoes&lt;/a&gt; as an example of how an artistic representation of them can pull together and have the power to &lt;em&gt;disclose&lt;/em&gt; a kind of life-world despite simply being ‘equipment.’ And it seems to me that a totally trashed pair of shoes does this very differently than a pair fresh out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wonder: when a thing’s lifespan as a thing is over (a lifespan determined in large part by its use context: i.e. a pair of boots that sits in a closet all year vs. pair used by a carpenter or roofer on worksites almost every day), what kind of lifespan does it acquire as something broken? How does the life of a &lt;em&gt;trash&lt;/em&gt; shoe different from a &lt;em&gt;shoe&lt;/em&gt; shoe, assuming that it’s possible these two shoes might &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; different things for me? An illustrative example would be something like comparing how we think of the ‘lifespan’ of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carsofamericainc.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/iStock_000013970322XSmall.jpg&quot;&gt;car battery&lt;/a&gt; with the ‘lifespan’ of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fullcarservice.org/images/category/carblog/carnews/bat_last/car-battery1.jpg&quot;&gt;dead car battery&lt;/a&gt;: the first has to do with human use, the possibility of travel, cold winter mornings, brand reliability, maintenance, usually a matter of years; the latter with molecular half-lives, recycling practices, landfills, all on a much longer scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sketch with the new pen, this of an abandoned vehicle, engine- and battery-less. With some color! (If you want to see the original I was trying to draw, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;http://i.ytimg.com/vi/j2SGlkFfH3Y/maxresdefault.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.23carintheweeds.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Car in the weeds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a kind of mythical image for me.  In his song &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomwaits.com/songs/song/368/Bad_As_Me/&quot;&gt;“Bad As Me”&lt;/a&gt; Tom Waits calls it simply “the car in the weeds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So two main questions: on the one hand, how do we conceive of time passing for things that are ‘invisible’ and ‘present-at-hand’ - things that are there in the background almost all the time, but that we take for granted until lost or broken? And on the other, how do we conceive of time passing for things that are out of sight &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; mind - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/06/26-trillion-pounds-of-garbage-where-does-the-worlds-trash-go/258234/&quot;&gt;things that have been cast aside&lt;/a&gt;, like this car is now, or my shoe soon will be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more: a pencil with a broken tip, and a pencil that has been sharpened way past its point of practical usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.23pencil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Broken pencil&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when things break, when their ‘time is up,’ they acquire a certain kind of urgency. They come to the fore. It’s almost like they come back into existence from some kind of constantly humming background noise. All of the sudden you have to decide what to do with this thing - do you fix it? Replace it with something else? Replace it with a new version of itself? Leave it in the weeds (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Pacific_garbage_patch&quot;&gt;or the center of the Pacific&lt;/a&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions may feel simple, or perhaps too straightforward, but they are the kinds of questions that matter for Daisen (us, humans, beings for whom being is a question) when it comes to things in our world. And because they matter to us in this way, these questions matter for how these objects &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;are not&lt;/em&gt; in our worlds - and by world I mean the highly contingent world with which a given person is familiar and in which they live their day-to-day lives, one that is changing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminds me of another scene from another 20th century novel, the “Time Passes” section of Virginia Woolf’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_the_Lighthouse&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;To the Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (much of which you can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=ng0Tg0FhRggC&amp;amp;q=time+passes#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=time%20passes&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;here on Google Books&lt;/a&gt;). Describing a home left more-or-less uninhabited for years, she writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“So with the house empty and the doors locked and the mattresses rolled round, those stray airs, advance guards of great armies, blustered in, brushed bare boards, nibbled and fanned, met nothing in bedroom or drawing-room that wholly resisted them but only hangings that flapped, wood that creaked, the bare legs of tables, saucepans and china already furred, tarnished, cracked. What people had shed and left - a pair of shoes, a shooting cap, some faded skirts and coats in wardrobes - those alone kept the human shape and in the emptiness indicated how once they were filled and animated; how once hands were busy with hooks and buttons; how once the looking-glass had held a face; had held a world hollowed out in which a figure turned, a hand flashed, the door opened, in came children rushing and tumbling; and went out again. … Loveliness and stillness clasped hands in the bedroom, and among the shrouded jugs and sheeted chairs even the prying of the wind, and the soft nose of the clammy sea airs, rubbing, snuffing, iterating, and reiterating their questions - “Will you fade? Will you perish?” - scarcely disturbed the peace, the indifference, the air of pure integrity, as if the question they asked scarcely needed that they should answer: we remain.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think more on just how my busted shoe, the car in the weeds, and the too-short pencil go about ‘remaining’ in the world, and how this might differ from their still-in-use counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 13:47:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/13: Time Pieces and Graphs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello all - three more images for Inktober.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a continuation from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;my previous Inktober post&lt;/a&gt;, very simply, two tubes of toothpaste, both almost empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.13toothpaste.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Empty toothpaste tubes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was still thinking of the consumption of objects, for two reasons: first, because of their importance to a historical thinker deeply interested in time (and on my orals list), one Karl Marx, who writes on everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch10.htm&quot;&gt;the length of the working day&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch01.htm#S1&quot;&gt;labour-time itself here in the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And second, because a lot of people use toothpaste in their everyday life. It is something they consume very slowly, and often even forget that they have or that it’s running out; they measure out its consumption bit by bit over the course of many weeks, but its presence over time is ‘at hand,’ or taken for granted in a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start with Marx though, in the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt; (titled: Commodities) he defines the value of a commodity as “the labour time socially necessary for its production.” He then goes on to quote himself from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1844/manuscripts/preface.htm&quot;&gt;Economic &amp;amp; Philosophic Manuscripts of 1844&lt;/a&gt; saying that “As exchange values, all commodities are merely definite quantities of &lt;em&gt;congealed labour-time&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a phrase! &lt;em&gt;Congealed labour-time&lt;/em&gt;. As though the object in hand were physically made up of hours from the lives of others. The idea that an hour of life itself can be estranged from an individual and sold for monetary compensation, and that these hours of others then congeal into an object which sits on my bathroom sink for a set number of weeks is fascinating, and which Marx thinks through seriously, though too much to talk about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second point though, that people use toothpaste everyday, has to do with the thinking of another philosopher I’ve been reading while studying for my oral exams - &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/&quot;&gt;Martin Heidegger&lt;/a&gt;. Though he’s interested &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#BeiTim&quot;&gt;in his big work&lt;/a&gt; about ontological questions (like, what kind of being does the number 1 have vs. the color brown, a chair, the solar system, a historical event, my cat, etc) he also believes that things ‘are’ for humans (or &lt;em&gt;Dasein&lt;/em&gt; in his terminology, the being for whom being is an issue or question) in a way that is more natural. In his thinking, when I see a desk, I don’t go for some abstract, philosophical, Aristotelian route and think of it as a substance with attributes (such as squareness or brownness), I think more of whether or not it is the right size, or close enough to a reading light, or if it is an heirloom that needs to be treated carefully. That these considerations actually make up, in many ways, the ‘being’ of the table itself for Dasein (humans) was fascinating to me when I first started reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence: toothpaste! I brush my teeth twice a day and use toothpaste from a tube that looks like one of these. It is something that fits in my hand and I can tell how much time I have left with this particular tube just by picking it up. Using a brand new tube is very different from the ones I have drawn here, crumpling up tubes to try to make them last, to &lt;em&gt;extend their lives&lt;/em&gt;. The “time” of a tube of toothpaste, its lifespan, is relatively slow (or long) compared to, say, a quart of milk or loaf of bread. The same tube persists through many weeks of use, and there is even a certain feeling of ‘letting go’ and beginning again when I have to stop crushing up an old familiar tube and go buy new. And trying a new brand, flavor, or type of toothpaste is a strangely serious time commitment, a decision that persists in your everyday experience (and teeth) for weeks or months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connects with another picture, those of time pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.13laptopwatchphone.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Time pieces&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to draw the things I look at during the day to tell what time it is. When this Dasein thinks of time (me), he probably thinks first of where he looks to ‘tell the time,’ the things I use to make sure that I am not late, or that I am getting enough sleep, or that I remember to eat lunch. For me these are my computer and my phone. My window into Greenwich Mean Time is almost always small numbers on a screen that sometimes fail to update to Daylight Savings. A lot of people have watches though, so I wanted to draw one of them too. I wonder how these objects of mediators of this standard time influence how time actually feels for the humans who use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is more abstract. I was thinking of Johanna Drucker’s work in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674724938&quot;&gt;Graphesis: Visual Forms of Knowledge Production&lt;/a&gt;, and particularly an article she wrote for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/&quot;&gt;DHQ&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html&quot;&gt;“Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display”&lt;/a&gt; in which she gives some examples of how humanists can use graphical representations. So I decided to draw some graphs about how we might experience time in a 24-hour period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.13graphs.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Time graphs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was envisioning that a given person would travel along the path of the line, x-axis being each hour passing, and y-axis being… something else. Experience? Not sure - point being, although the same number of ‘hours’ passed for each line, the length, trajectory, and experience of each line (or sets of lines) was very unique. Would love to draw some more of these, or at least think through them a little more seriously before the month is out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 13:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/5: Three Sketches</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wanted to put up a few time sketches for our own version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mrjakeparker.com/inktober&quot;&gt;Inktober&lt;/a&gt;. I’m aiming for every other day or so, so here’s three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three have to do with time and consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.5.movietime.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Popcorn movie time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love going to the movies, and usually opt for the biggest popcorn possible (bucket) but wonder how differently and quickly the ‘time of eating’ passes depending on how big your eating vessel is (I’m sure plenty of others have written about this - just Googling around quickly I found an entire website dedicated to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smallplatemovement.org/&quot;&gt;using smaller plates&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.5pintbythehour.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Pint by pint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one is another thing some people do to pass time together - having a drink at a bar or restaurant, which can go slow or fast. Here I tried to draw the rings that beer leaves behind as a marker of how much time passed where for the beer in this particular glass. Beer time! Reminds me of &lt;a href=&quot;http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Slughorn&#39;s_Hourglass&quot;&gt;Slughorn’s Hourglass&lt;/a&gt; in Harry Potter, which goes faster or slower depending on the quality of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inktober/10.5cigarettebreak.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Cigarette break&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is a cigarette - read a poem for orals by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/sherman-alexie&quot;&gt;Sherman Alexie&lt;/a&gt; with James Dean in it (called “Tourists”), got me thinking of the images of Dean &lt;a href=&quot;http://images.amcnetworks.com/blogs.amctv.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/2jacket.jpg&quot;&gt;with a cigarette in his red jacket&lt;/a&gt; (no color in that photo, but pretty sure that’s the jacket) and got thinking of how so many people frame “breaks” from their day, little slices of time, around something like cigarette “breaks.” As though they were carrying a pack of minutes in their pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 13:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time and Praxis 2015-2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Time is a massive concept. If you were asked to think about it – how it works, feels, changes, what it looks like, how people go about talking about it, or representing it – where would you start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a person interested and invested in critical theory, my initial reflex would be to go to philosophers, phenomenologists – writers like &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#TemTem&quot;&gt;Martin Heidegger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/merleau-ponty/&quot;&gt;Maurice Merleau-Ponty&lt;/a&gt;, and so on. Or check in with narrative theorists, think again about what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%A9rard_Genette#Order&quot;&gt;Gérard Genette&lt;/a&gt; says about time and narrative in Narrative Discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second reflex would be to look at art and cultural objects. I’ve been trying to watch and/or reconsider as many time-travel movies as I had time for, everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4CC60HJvZRE&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8wqVHjK2bQs&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Donnie Darko&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to something more straightforward like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c4Jo8QoOTQ4&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Terminator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes you find something unexpected – for example, trying to &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/657/&quot;&gt;untangle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Primer&lt;/em&gt; after watching it last week, Gillet (a fellow Praxis member) commented that manipulating time in films can have a certain scare-factor, almost like it’s a specific branch of horror movies. I’d never thought about it that way before. Time, and the manipulation of time, has the power to frighten us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, games: like &lt;a href=&quot;http://braid-game.com/&quot;&gt;Braid&lt;/a&gt;, where manipulating time is the only way to solve puzzles and progress through the narrative. Or (at Jeremy’s suggestion) checking out Ian Bogost’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://bogost.com/games/aslowyear/&quot;&gt;A Slow Year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, literature. I thought first to a classics like H.G. Wells’ 1895 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Time_Machine&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Time Machine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or Ray Bradbury’s 1952 short story &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Sound_of_Thunder&quot;&gt;“A Sound of Thunder,”&lt;/a&gt; where tourist big-game hunters go back in time to kill dinosaurs, but (spoilers) someone accidentally steps on a butterfly and changes the whole course of history. Then to Kurt Vonnegut’s 1969 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slaughterhouse-Five&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse Five&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (probably because it’s the first book I ever wrote a book report on), where a character becomes “unstuck in time” as he dips in and out of his life experiences. Or even to something like Ruth Ozeki’s 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ruthozeki.com/writing-film/a-tale-for-the-time-being/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Tale for the Time Being&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (which I’m reading for my oral exams), where relationships with past and present “time beings” might, in some ways, influence one another, even when those cross-temporal relationships are mediated textually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many movies, games, novels, short stories, poems, and plays I could go to here it’s nuts – not even looking at works with entangled narrative structures like the film &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0209144/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memento&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or Faulkner’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Absalom,_Absalom!&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Absalom, Absalom!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (for example). These above are just the first that come to mind, each of which interacts with time and experiences time a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first time writing here as a Praxis Fellow for the 2015-2016 year. Along with &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/charter-2015-2016/&quot;&gt;producing a charter&lt;/a&gt;, this year we’re all trying to think about time in as many different ways as possible, staying wide open with it and willing to explore any new possibilities, each coming at it from our own unique angle. Throughout the year, in our work and in posts like this, I’ll try to keep track of and share what I feel like I am able to bring to our work from my own unique perspective (apparently even if sometimes that means just talking about a bunch of time-travel stories I’m excited about). We’re only a few weeks in, and I can already say how excited I am to be working with the Praxis team and all the folks at the Scholars’ Lab this coming year. I can’t wait to see what we come up with!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/09/24/praxis_and_time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://reedeth.github.io/blog/2015/09/24/praxis_and_time.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
