<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethan Reed</title>
    <description>Personal blog of Ethan Reed, PhD Candidate in English Literature at the University of Virginia.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 17:46:59 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 17:46:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Transcription is Complicated</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted with minor changes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/transcription-is-complicated/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent &lt;em&gt;PMLA&lt;/em&gt; issue on digital methods, Johanna Drucker concludes her article &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mlajournals.org/doi/abs/10.1632/pmla.2017.132.3.628&quot;&gt;“Why Distant Reading Isn’t”&lt;/a&gt; by claiming that distant reading’s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;literalness makes it the closest form of reading imaginable. What distant reading lacks is distance. That distance is critical; it is the space between the literal text and the virtual text, between the inscriptional, notational surface and the rhetorical, cognitive effect that produces a text. (633)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, when an algorithm “reads” a corpus by scouring it for patterns of one kind or another, it doesn’t transform the text the way that a human reader does. It can get so “close” because it reads without the powerful and dynamic cognitive filters through which human readers conjure, out of the written word, literary worlds. For Drucker, closing the gap between “reader” and text in this way is one of the things that makes distant reading “the closest form of reading imaginable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, crucially, human decisions shape how a program closes that gap in the first place. As Drucker argues elsewhere in the article, “modeling and paramaterization”—decisions made by scholars and programmers as to what a program will look for and, therefore, be able to find—not only “shape the terms by which a text is analyzed to produce quantitative data,” but are also “rendered almost invisible by the forms in which results are expressed” (632). These before-the-fact decisions, then, are what allow an algorithm to read from such a close range—ignoring the “rhetorical, cognitive effect that produces a text,” they engage with “the inscriptional, notational surface” according to a set of pre-established instructions to produce results of one form or another. In this sense, some might argue that the “distance” distant reading “lacks” is the gap in which literature happens: the unpredictable, unwieldy interpretive space in which a reader transforms text on a page or screen into a living work of art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transcription&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I assemble my corpus of poetry from the Black Arts Movement, I’ve grown more interested in this gap between “inscriptional, notational surface” and “rhetorical, cognitive effect.” In the past three weeks I have transcribed approximately twenty books of poetry. This is, in many ways, the kind of “reading” that we expect a machine to be good at: tedious and time-consuming, sure, but also mechanical, even mindless—something lacking that human “distance” Drucker describes above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to transcription, however, the devil is in the details. And anyone familiar with using OCR software to transcribe text from images knows that machines still struggle to get all the details right. After scanning pages into images and processing them with a program like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abbyy.com/en-us/finereader/&quot;&gt;ABBYY FineReader&lt;/a&gt;, the resulting text files are often garbled with mistakes—errors that require a human reviewer to identify, compare with the original, and correct by hand. Though an extremely useful piece of software, a program can’t be all things to all people, and I found this especially true for experimental texts like the poetry in my corpus that employ unusual indentation, spacing, punctuation, capitalization, and non-traditional spellings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I already knew that ABBYY FineReader would have trouble transcribing text from images from my corpus. That’s one of the reasons I decided to transcribe them by hand in the first place. What I didn’t anticipate was how much trouble I—a presumably well-trained human reader—would have transcribing text from physical documents into a text editor. This being the case even when my documents were fully intact and the text completely legible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the past few weeks, I found that this hairs-breadth, closest-form-of-reading-imaginable reading—the kind that seems to go no further than inscriptional surface—is also a complex task requiring creativity, imagination, and resourcefulness. Moreover, rather than being a mindless or merely mechanical task, the transcription of these texts frequently presented thorny decisions that demanded my judgement as a reader, scholar, and programmer. Arriving at these decisions often required not only a knowledge of digital methods, but also of bibliographical methods, questions of poetic form, and more practical project management skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spacing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, lines from “a/coltrane/poem,” the final poem from Sonia Sanchez’s 1970 collection &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt; (and a poem that got me listening to Coltrane’s music while transcribing):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;         (soft       rise up blk/people.  rise up blk/people
         chant)   RISE.  &amp;amp;  BE.  what u can. &lt;br /&gt;
                         MUST BE.BE.BE.BE.BE.BE.BE.BE-E-E-E-E- &lt;br /&gt;
                                                           BE-E-E-E-E-E-
                                        yeh. john coltrane. &lt;br /&gt;
         my favorite things is u.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many of the poems from &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt;, “a/coltrane/poem” makes dramatic use of indentation, punctuation, the spaces between words, and the spaces between lines. Even transcribing these lines to be published here on the Scholars’ Lab WordPress site, however, raises a number of technical and practical issues. For example, there is no easy way to produce this kind of whitespace in HTML. When web browsers parse the whitespace in poetry—indentation, tabs, etc.—they more or less get rid of it. While investigating the poetry of Mina Loy, Andrew Pilsch argues in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palgrave.com/us/book/9781137595683&quot;&gt;his chapter in &lt;em&gt;Reading Modernism with Machines &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;that “the nature of HTML resists—even &lt;em&gt;prevents&lt;/em&gt;—the easy introduction of … typographic experimentation” (245)—something he discusses earlier on &lt;a href=&quot;https://andrew.pilsch.com/blog/2014/06/24/mina-loy-online-we-turn-into-machines/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;. Like Pilsch, I ended up having to make use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-breaking_space&quot;&gt;the “&amp;amp;nbsp” space&lt;/a&gt;—something Pilsch discusses more in-depth—to shoehorn spaces into the poem so it would appear correctly, I hope, in web browsers. This means that, in HTML, the above section of poetry looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;(soft&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;rise up blk/people.&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;rise up blk/people
&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;chant)&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;RISE.&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;amp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;BE.&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;what u can.
&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;MUST BE.BE.BE.BE.BE.BE.BE.BE-E-E-E-E-
&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;BE-E-E-E-E-E-
&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;yeh. john coltrane.
&lt;span class=&quot;ni&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;my favorite things is u.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, a complete mess. But before trying to print parts of this poem in HTML through WordPress, at an even more basic level I had to get it into a text editor, a process which also raised a number of questions requiring practical decisions. As I type out the above lines into Atom, I have to ask: how many spaces should separate the words that seem to be a stage direction on the left— “(soft / … / chant)”—from the words on the right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world, I would have access to all materials used by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.broadsidelotuspress.org/dudley-randall-broadside-press&quot;&gt;Dudley Randall’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmich.edu/library/clarke/AccessMaterials/Bibliographies/DetroitBroadsidePress/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;Broadside Press&lt;/a&gt; to publish this 1970 edition, as well as publication materials from all subsequent editions. Comparing these various documents, I would be able to get a better sense of the typographical materials and units of measurement used to represent Sanchez’s poem on paper. This would provide me with a more holistic sense of how to represent Sanchez’s poem in my text editor. However, given constraints on my time and resources as a Ph.D. student, as well as the size of my corpus, deciding how deep I want to dig in the archive to answer such questions requires serious consideration. Moreover, as far as I can tell, while there were printings of this edition of &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt; as late as 1973, there were no other new editions of the work—so the edition I have is the only one I have to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when faced with the question—how many spaces should separate these words in a text file?—I looked at how far a space gets me in relation to other characters, gauged this against the kinds of spaces in poems elsewhere in the book, and made an educated guess: three after “(soft”, and one after “chant)”. The same goes for the space between “&amp;amp;  BE.”, which is slightly larger than the gaps separating most other words. I’m not sure exactly how much larger this gap is, so I make another educated guess, giving it two spaces instead of one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a multiple-page poem defined by such visual experimentation, however, trying to measure and align every word, space, and line break so that the text in my text editor resembles the text on the page—even roughly—is a real challenge. In some cases, given the functionalities of the editor I’m working with, this challenge becomes an impasse. Even in the example above: the space separating the line “yeh. john coltrane.” from the preceding line—“BE-E-E-E-E-E-”—matches the size of other line breaks within stanzas in this volume. But the space separating this line from its succeeding line—“my favorite things is u.”—is both larger than line breaks within stanzas and smaller than breaks indicating new stanzas. While transcribing, I normally represent adjacent lines in a poem with adjacent lines in my text editor; I represent stanza breaks with an empty line. How do I represent in my text editor a line break that is effectively 1.5 times the size of a normal line break? Without reworking my entire spacing system across all of my poems, I can’t—so I decided to transcribe them as adjacent lines despite the clearly visible difference on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textual Scholarship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of these challenges would come as no surprise to scholars—like Drucker—interested in textual study, bibliographical study, and scholarly editing. Having had the great fortune of taking a seminar here at UVA on textual criticism and scholarly editing with David Vander Meulen, &lt;a href=&quot;http://rarebookschool.org/courses/history/h50/&quot;&gt;a course at the Rare Book School&lt;/a&gt; on the book in the American industrial era with Michael Winship, as well as many thoughtful conversations with friend, colleague, and textual scholar James Ascher, I’ve had the opportunity to adopt many of these methodological lenses as my own. These lenses help us to ask questions like: what exactly, is a literary work? Is Sanchez’s &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt; the words printed in ink on the pages of the physical book I’m holding? If there are discrepancies between this book and later editions, how do we reconcile them? And, more relevant to my current project, how does the digital copy of this work in my text editor differ from the bound copy held at UVA’s library from which I’m making my transcription?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In considering these questions, I find helpful the vocabulary used by textual scholar G.T. Tanselle that distinguishes between &lt;em&gt;document&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;text&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;. To offer a greatly reduced shorthand for Tanselle’s nuanced thinking on these distinctions: there are &lt;em&gt;texts of works&lt;/em&gt; and there are &lt;em&gt;texts of documents&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Texts of documents&lt;/em&gt; refer to the words, markings, or inscriptions on a physical object that is completely unique though it may seem to be identical to other artifacts. &lt;em&gt;Texts of works&lt;/em&gt;, on the other hand, are slightly more complicated—they consider the words as instructions for performing that intangible thing that is a verbal literary work in the minds of readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though they may seem abstract, conceptual distinctions such as these have emerged from some of the most concrete, hands-on, rubber-meets-the-road scholarship in literary thought—for example, the kind of thinking that goes into examining multiple versions of a work (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Lear#Date_and_text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;King Lear&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) so as to produce a single scholarly edition. A distinction like Tanselle’s between texts of documents and texts of works offers a guiding light for scholar down in the often bewildering weeds of a given archive. As Tanselle argues in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/40371919&quot;&gt;“Textual Criticism and Deconstruction,”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The distinction between the texts of documents (handwritten or printed, private or published) and the texts of works is basic to textual criticism. The effort to “reconstruct” or “establish” the texts of works presupposes that the texts we find in documents cannot automatically be equated with the texts of the works that those documents claim to be conveying. (1)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, scholars must exercise a great deal of judgement as they try to reconcile meaningful—and sometimes extremely significant—discrepancies between versions of a given physical text as found in physical documents in their efforts to determine the text of the work itself. The role that “intentions” play in all this— as in the words that were meant to be put down—and how best to account for the mediating forces and actors at work in the publication of a book, is a point of debate in textual scholarship, often dependent on the kinds of research questions one hopes to investigate (for more reading here, see D F. McKenzie’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/bibliography-and-the-sociology-of-texts/CF5FE52FD90E0B79D8583FF675C4923D&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Jerome McGann’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.princeton.edu/titles/4894.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Textual Condition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and Tanselle’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/40371938&quot;&gt;“Textual Criticism and Literary Sociology”&lt;/a&gt;). And as many scholars have argued, these conceptual distinctions central to textual criticism and thought extend to digital artifacts as well—see, for example, Matthew Kirschenbaum’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000151/000151.html&quot;&gt;“.txtual condition.”&lt;/a&gt; Scholarship such as this helps me to think through how a hand-typed .txt file of &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt; relates to a physical codex made of paper and ink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stanza Breaks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, part of the purpose of this post is to expand on just how complicated transcription can be when it comes to performing text analysis on a literary corpus. Moreover, I’m hoping to think through how these practices are bound up with traditional bibliographical lines of inquiry. In short, I’m hoping here to offer further examples of how reading a literary text at extremely close range—Drucker’s “inscriptional, notational surface”—involves all kinds of human thought and judgement. Even if this thought and judgement are hidden in things we might take for granted—like the distinction between thinking of the book I’m holding as being Sonia Sanchez’s &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt;, as opposed to a unique physical document inscribed with a text that intends to convey &lt;em&gt;We A BaddDDD People&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to offer a couple more examples of typographical concerns that came up during my transcription process. Unlike extra spaces between words in a line, these issues also more directly impact the kinds of results my analysis aims to produce, as they impact what “counts” as a line or stanza in my model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first has to do with stanza breaks. In my day-to-day reading practice, identifying a stanza break usually feels straightforward: lines grouped together in a poem, probably separated by white space. Digging a little deeper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.princeton.edu/titles/9677.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry &amp;amp; Poetics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; begins its entry by defining a stanza as “a unit of poetic lines organized by a specific principle or set of principles” (1358). Likewise, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780199208272.001.0001/acref-9780199208272-e-1080?rskey=bxV0Ev&amp;amp;result=1081&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;he Oxford Dictionary of Literary Terms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; defines a stanza first and foremost as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;A group of verse lines forming a section of a poem and sharing the same structure as all or some of the other sections of the same poem, in terms of the lengths of its lines, its metre, and usually its rhyme scheme. In printed poems, stanzas are separated by spaces.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this definition doesn’t help us much with something like Sanchez’s “a/coltrane/poem”—a poem that more or less flies in the face of traditional stanzaic form—it does seem like it would help us if we wanted to make a “stanza” a parameter in our analytical models, or even in figuring out how best to separate lines and stanzas in our text files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even in more traditionally stanzaic poems—of which there are many in my corpus—deciding what “counts” as a stanza can get messy. Something as simple as page breaks, for instance, can wreak havoc in making such decisions. This is particularly the case when only one edition of a work exists, and one doesn’t have access to original manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider, for example, a poem titled “Malcolm Spoke/  who listened?” from Haki R. Madhubuti’s 1969 collection &lt;em&gt;Don’t Cry, Scream&lt;/em&gt;, published with Broadside Press. The poem is stanzaic, and distinguishes stanzas with what seem to me like normal breaks. These groupings, however, have no regular rhyme scheme, no regular use of capitalization, no regular number of lines, no tight thematic or narrative structure (i.e. a point of view that alternates from stanza to stanza), and no regular pattern in punctuation (i.e. some stanzas conclude with no punctuation while some conclude with a period). And, crucially, the poem extends partway onto a second page. These are the two groups of lines on either side of the page break:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;animals come in all colors. &lt;br /&gt;
dark meat will roast as fast as whi-te meat &lt;br /&gt;
[PAGE BREAK] &lt;br /&gt;
especially in &lt;br /&gt;
the unitedstatesofamerica’s &lt;br /&gt;
new &lt;br /&gt;
self-cleaning ovens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a few reasons, I decided to transcribe these two sections as a single stanza. First, at a more visual, design level, the poem has no other stanzas as short as two lines. The book as a whole, in fact, has very few two-line stanzas, and while there are a few single unattached lines, they usually come right at the end of a poem. In comparison with the rest of the poem and the other poems in the collection, then, it seemed more likely to be a larger stanza than not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More convincingly, however, my feeling that these two chunks are one unit comes from the poem itself—the group of lines above seems, to me, to develop a coherent line of poetic thought. The first two lines introduce the metaphor of meat of “all colors” roasting, and the following line (after the page break) intensifies this imagery by locating this metaphor in the United States and its “new /self-cleaning ovens.” The lines after the page break make most grammatical and metaphorical sense when taken as part and parcel of the lines prior to the page break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that other poems in this volume don’t break up grammatical expressions across stanzas—they definitely do. Other poems in this volume also develop specific metaphors or images over the course of several stanzas. But with this poem in particular, stanzas seem to be doing something else. Each has a kind of conceptual focus—they stand alongside one another as evenly-weighted, coherent units of expression. For example, the stanza preceding the one quoted above is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;the double-breasted hipster
has been replaced with a
dashiki wearing rip-off
who went to city college
majoring in physical education.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stanza develops, from line to line, a description of—and stance towards—this “dashiki wearing rip-off” who replaces the “double-breasted hipster.” Each line builds on the last, slowly unfolding different aspects of how one figure “has been replaced” with another: the speaker discloses a skeptical attitude towards these figures, identified by what they wear, where they went to school, and what they studied. Like the stanza with the page break, this group of lines seems to me to develop a coherent line of thought that doesn’t spill over into subsequent stanzas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding these stanzas in light of the poem as a whole, then, aligns with this reading: the rhythm of the poem as it moves from stanza to stanza seems to emerge from a feeling of moving from one idea to the next—and, for me as a reader, breaking this group of lines at the page break into two different stanzas feels like it disrupts that rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could certainly be argued that the group of lines with the page break was meant to be two stanzas specifically so as to disrupt the rhythm of this stanzaic form—that such a disruption is vital to the poem’s meaning. But, as is the case with scholarly editing, I had to make a judgement call to proceed with my project. So I considered everything I knew, tried to find out more if possible, and made the best decision I could given what I had in front of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Runovers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last example. Lines of poetry can get very long. Sometimes, lines get too long for the physical documents on which they’re inscribed. During an enlightening conversation with Jahan Ramazani on this and many other issues addressed in this post, he gave me the example of editing &lt;em&gt;The Norton Anthology of Modern and Contemporary Poetry&lt;/em&gt; and having to print and number the extremely long lines of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/49303/howl&quot;&gt;Allen Ginsberg’s “Howl.”&lt;/a&gt; Central to this decision-making process was considering standard practice on what the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/16/ch13/ch13_toc.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chicago Manual of Style&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; calls “Long lines and runovers in poetry.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;CMS&lt;/em&gt; defines runovers as “the remainder of lines too long to appear as a single line,” which are “usually indented one em from the line above.” In other words, when lines get too long—as in Ginsberg’s poetry, or Walt Whitman’s—a hanging indent about an em-dash in length tells the reader that the line was too long for the book. The entry concludes, however, by indicating that it might not always be so clear when an indentation is a runover and when it’s a new line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Runover lines, although indented, should be distinct from new lines deliberately indented by the poet … Generally, a unique and uniform indent for runovers will be enough to accomplish this.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen already just in this post, much of poetry in my corpus rebels against traditional poetic form, including standard indentation and spacing practices. Determining whether or not a group of words is one or two lines, however, is extremely important for my project. The “line” is the basic unit I’ve been asking sentiment analysis tools in TextBlob and NLTK to evaluate for sentiment. In short: what counts as a line really matters, and ambiguities surrounding runovers could very well add up to have a significant impact on the results of my analyses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An excellent example of this appears a few pages earlier in Madhubuti’s &lt;em&gt;Don’t Cry, Scream&lt;/em&gt;, in a poem titled “Gwendolyn Brooks.” The poem &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/50782/gwendolyn-brooks&quot;&gt;is available online&lt;/a&gt; through the Poetry Foundation, and it appears in my physical copy as it does on this website, indentations and all. Halfway through the poem there is a distinct sequence, over a dozen lines long, that lists a series of portmanteaus describing different kinds of “black”—from “360degreesblack” to “blackisbeautifulblack” and “i justdiscoveredblack.” Over the course of this sequence, there are three indented lines, each one-word long, that interrupt the otherwise steady stream of images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first bluff, these lines struck me as runovers. The list-like nature of the lines felt like they lent themselves to running a little long—as we see with a poet like Whitman, once a list starts, it can just keep going and going. Moreover, no thematic or poetic reason jumped out at me as to why someone might indent these words as opposed to any others. Of course, there is the possibility that such indentations were completely on purpose, and are part of a project to disrupt and transform any resonance with someone like Whitman and the canon he represents. Sitting in front of my computer, a little bleary-eyed from all the transcribing, I honestly wasn’t sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I began looking for other appearances of the poem. The version published by the Poetry Foundation complicated my initial thought that these one-word indented lines were runovers. Jahan Ramazani also suggested that, given the importance of anthologies to the Black Arts Movement, even if a book has no later editions, individual poems therein might appear somewhere in a collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a realization, however, presents another fork in the road of my research. As a researcher committed to being as thoughtful and thorough as possible as I work with the poetry from a revolutionary art movement, I am delighted to know that I still might be able to pursue questions that I thought would remain unanswered (i.e., “is this a runover line or two separate lines?”). As a researcher with limited resources, however, I have to decide whether or not pursuing these questions will be the best use of my time and energy in this particular project. There are a lot of anthologies containing poetry from the Black Arts Movement out there, so I have to weigh the time it would take to locate and look through them all for instances of those poems from my ~20 book corpus that may have runover lines, against the potential impact it would have on the results of the analyses I hope to perform. As it currently stands, I’ve made a note of this particular ambiguity and plan to reassess what I should do with it and others like it after assembling the rest of the corpus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this post has hopefully shown, transcribing texts from book to screen can get very tricky. More than a simple act of mechanical reproduction, it can stump us with questions about literary works that seem to have no discernible answers. From one moment to the next, it can demand a working knowledge of bibliographical methods; digital methods; aesthetic form; and how to manage a project’s resources. And—as Drucker above argues regarding text analysis more generally—navigating these questions requires rigorous human judgement every step of the way. Even in situations where the practicalities of project management and the realities of our textual archive make this judgement feel all-too-fallible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other, important aspects of this human judgement which I haven’t had time to think through as much as I would like to have in this post. For example, digging deeper into those questions explored by Andrew Pilsch mentioned above that investigate the challenging ways in which web browsers are designed to parse the whitespace in poetry in HTML. Or, how the default parameters of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/_modules/nltk/tokenize.html&quot;&gt;the basic tokenizing packages in NLTK&lt;/a&gt; throw away whitespace—the idea that the programmers behind these text analysis technologies view their standard use as most likely to focus on text, not the spaces between text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very long story short: transcription is complicated! And I hope this post has done something to foreground some of those invisible, behind-the-scenes decisions that—like modeling and parameterization—give shape to the results a text analysis project produces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2018/02/21/transcription-is-complicated.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2018/02/21/transcription-is-complicated.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First Steps with NLP and a Collection of Amiri Baraka&#39;s Poetry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted with minor changes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/first-steps-with-nlp-and-a-collection-of-amiri-barakas-poetry/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amiri Baraka’s &lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt;, 1969&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll discuss my initial foray into natural language processing (NLP)—cleaning up a corpus and prepping it for some basic text analysis techniques. I want to begin, however, with a note on the small textual corpus that I’m using in these preliminary explorations—&lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt;, a 1969 collection of three books of poetry by Amiri Baraka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a prefatory note to the collection, Baraka offers an “Explanation of the Work” that touches on the three books of poetry contained within. “&lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;,” he writes of the first book, “meant I had come to see the superstructure of filth Americans call their way of life, and wanted to see it fall. To sabotage it,” in a word. The second book, he argues, takes this intensity even further: “But &lt;em&gt;Target Study&lt;/em&gt; is trying to really study, like bomber crews do the soon to be destroyed cities. Less passive now, less uselessly ‘literary.’” If these comments are any indication, the poetry of &lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt; has a certain level of emotional and political intensity. These poems articulate rage—they thunder, fulminate, and protest, venting a vindicated anger at racial injustice in America. Others simmer with a more restrained heat, but still tend to employ an often unsettling rhetorical violence. Consider, for example, the conclusion of a poem from &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt; titled “A POEM SOME PEOPLE WILL HAVE TO UNDERSTAND”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have awaited the coming of a natural &lt;br /&gt;
phenomenon. Mystics and romantics, knowledgeable &lt;br /&gt;
workers &lt;br /&gt;
of the land. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But none has come. &lt;br /&gt;
(repeat) &lt;br /&gt;
but none has come. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Will the machinegunners please step forward?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though startling, this final image punctuates a familiar narrative: the mounting of frustration, the boiling over of feeling while waiting and waiting for justice. The speaker’s closing remark seems to respond to the question asked in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/46548/harlem&quot;&gt;Langston Hughes’s poem “Harlem”&lt;/a&gt;—”What happens to a dream deferred?”—but raises the ante of the inquiry, and shifts from Hughes’s suggestive but still open-ended conclusion (“&lt;em&gt;Or does it explode?&lt;/em&gt;”) to an unsettling direct request (“Will the machinegunners please step forward?”). The poem also, however, seems aware of its high dramatic tone: it conveys the gravity of this deferred deliverance with somewhat formal rhetoric like “We have awaited” and “But none has come”, but highlights—and perhaps undercuts—its own theatricality by embedding a stage direction in the poem, “(repeat)”. We’ve waited for long enough, the poem seems to argue, but stages this claim in such a way that the final line’s delivery hangs suspended somewhere between deadpan and dead serious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: a heightened revolutionary rhetoric permeates the poems in this collection. Many have noted, however, that a troubling violence permeates them as well. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/1512315?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;one scholar describes&lt;/a&gt; “Black Art”—one of the most graphic but also most well-known poems from this collection—as “a difficult poem in its race and gender violence, in its violence against peoples.” In the 1991 &lt;em&gt;The Leroi Jones/Amiri Baraka Reader&lt;/em&gt;, editor William J. Harris describes &lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt; as a collection in which Baraka “traces his painful exit from the white world and his entry into blackness,” an “exorcism of white consciousness and values [that] included a ten-year period of professed hatred of whites, and most especially jews [sic].” Baraka looks back at this period in &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Z-C4E3zdBxkC&amp;amp;q=snarling#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22struggling%20to%20be%20born%22&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;his 1984 autobiography&lt;/a&gt; at a remove from the red-hot intensity of the poems themselves: “I guess, during this period, I got the reputation for being a snarling, white-hating madman. There was some truth to it, because I was struggling to be born, to break out from the shell I could instinctively sense surrounded my own dash for freedom.” From this perspective, this is the violence of escape, of “struggling to be born” from within a constricting “shell”—a version, perhaps, of the violence of the deferred dream that explodes at the end of Langston Hughes’s poem “Harlem.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initial Steps with NLP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a scholar interested in articulations of anger, resentment, and frustration with injustice—particularly injustice of a systemic and institutional nature—as well as digital methodologies, I thought these texts in particular might be worth looking at more closely with NLP techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a graduate student working in a period that is almost entirely still in copyright, however, &lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt; also interested me because it is a small corpus of works—three books of poetry—to which I currently have access through UVA. Though conceptually unglamorous, basic questions of access have played an enormous role in determining the initial paths in my scholarly decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sense, though assembling workable data is always a challenge, scholars interested in literary texts prior to the early 20th century have more options for readily accessible textual corpora. For 20th- and 21st-century scholars interested in textual analysis, however, questions of copyright have made finding openly available textual data from which a corpus could be built an extremely difficult task: while able to share results of analyses through transformative, non-consumptive use, scholars of these periods cannot share the corpora from which these insights are drawn. This presents additional challenges in terms of reproducibility as well as in the already long, labor-intensive task of assembling, cleaning, and prepping a corpus prior to any actual application of NLP techniques. If texts aren’t already available as text files through a university or institution, they either have to be typed out by hand or scanned page by page, run through optical recognition software that transforms the page image into text, then also ultimately cleaned and corrected by hand. In short: no preexisting corpora means no experiments, prototypes, or conceptual ventures without surmounting certain barriers to entry that often prove time- or cost-prohibitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this project, even though UVA has access to the 1969 edition of &lt;em&gt;Black Magic: Collected Poetry 1961-1967&lt;/em&gt;, the text isn’t ready for NLP out-of-the-box. The page contained a lot of text beyond that of the literary work in question: page numbers, line numbers, bibliographical information, headers and footers, all kinds of weird punctuation, and so on. For example, the title of the first poem in &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;, “Three Modes of History and Culture,” appeared in this electronic edition as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Baraka, Imamu Amiri, 1934- : Three Modes of History and Culture [from Black Magic: Collected Poetry 1961-1967 (1969) , The Bobbs-Merrill Company ]&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To perform sentiment analysis on &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;, then, I first needed to get the raw text. By “raw text” I mean a big bag of all of &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;’s words. My goal initially was to get this bag of words with no line numbers, no punctuation, no capitalized first letters (otherwise Python would think they were two different words), and no spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone doing this work for the first time, I felt like I could handle writing a program that would remove capital letters, get the txt file into the correct file-type, maybe even get rid of the line numbers. But what about all this clutter surrounding the title of each poem? I considered how I might remove this with a program, but even something as small as irregular line breaks means the words would be chopped up in slightly different ways each time. Given the size of the corpus, I decided it would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/1319/&quot;&gt;wiser to remove the clutter by hand&lt;/a&gt; than to write a one-time program that automated it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a huge assist from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/brandon-walsh/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, cleaning up the rest of the text with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/&quot;&gt;Natural Language Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; (NLTK) was relatively straightforward. We wrote a small Python script that removed line numbers, then proceeded to write a script that would prep the clutter-free text files for text analysis, first by reading the text file as a list of lines &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;, then by tokenizing that list of lines into a list of lists, where each sub-list is a list of the words that make up a line &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;get_raw_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Given a filename, get the raw text&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;r&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;raw_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;readlines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;raw_text&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;tokenize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Given raw text that is a list of lines, produce the tokens&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line_tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line_tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nltk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;word_tokenize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line_tokens&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this may seem kind of complicated, certain kinds of text analysis need the lines to be tokenized in this way—much of the work then involves getting the text to be the right kind of data type (list of words, list of lists, etc.) for a given kind of analysis. Because I’m interested in sentiment analysis, I also needed to make every word lowercase &lt;strong&gt;(3)&lt;/strong&gt;, remove punctuation &lt;strong&gt;(4)&lt;/strong&gt;, and remove spaces &lt;strong&gt;(5)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(3)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;lowercase&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;all_tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Given the tokenized text, lowercase everything&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lower&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;each_token&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;each_token&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;all_tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_tokens&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(4)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;no_punctuation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Given the lowercased text, remove punctuation&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;join&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;punctuation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(5)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;no_spaces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Given the text without punctuation, remove empty items from lists&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having written out all these functions, we then made a new function that called on each of them one after the other, running through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-is-natural-language-processing-pipeline&quot;&gt;the pipeline of activities&lt;/a&gt; necessary for NLP (our notes-to-self included):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# get a filename&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# get raw text&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# preprocess that text:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# 1. tokenize&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# 2. lowercase&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# 3. Get rid of punctuation&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# 4. get rid of white space&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# segment if you care (if you care about sentences,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#   lines, stanzas, poems)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# tag with parts of speech&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# do the stuff you actually care about&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;corpus/black_magic_clean.txt&#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;raw_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get_raw_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tokenize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;raw_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lower_tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lowercase&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;without_punct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;no_punctuation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lower_tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;without_spaces&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;no_spaces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;without_punct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it gets the job done, this code is clunky. It represents, in short, the first steps in my learning how NLP works. And while not the most elegant in terms of form or function, writing steps out in this way was conceptually clear to me as someone trying them for the first time. I also want to add that throughout much of this Brandon and I were practicing something called pair programming, with Brandon at the keyboard (or “driving”) and me observing, asking questions, and discussing different ways of doing things. In addition to being an exciting scholarly investigation, this project is also a learning experience for me, and our code-decision-making process often reflects that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more on the intricacies of collaboration later. To recap, at this point I had a series of functions that, in a linear, step-by-step fashion, took my original text file and began to play with them in Python’s working memory: it took Amiri Baraka’s poetry as one data type (a giant string of words) and turned it into another (a tokenized list of lists), with some changes along the way (like lowercasing and getting rid of punctuation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made this so clunky, however, stemmed in large part from how I had organized my tasks: I gave Python basically only one thing to think about and work with at a time. It would take my corpus, W, and turn it into X, which it would then turn into Y, and then Z, and so on. But if I wanted Python to remember X while it was working on Z, I had to write code to turn Z &lt;em&gt;back into&lt;/em&gt; X—in short, a data-type nightmare. Which sounds pretty abstract, but presented all kinds of practical problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, after having gotten all the way to Z—my lowercased, punctuation-free list of lists—I wanted to try a basic form of text analysis I had seen in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/book/ch02.html&quot;&gt;an early chapter of the NLTK book&lt;/a&gt; (called stylistics) in which I compared the use of different modal verbs in the three books of Baraka’s poetry. The only way I knew how to do this was to run a frequency distribution on a giant list of words—which means I had to &lt;em&gt;un&lt;/em&gt;-tokenize my nicely tokenized texts, basically jumping from Z back to W. So I wrote some clunky code that let me do so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;frequency1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Given the lists without any empty slots, turn the thing into one giant list of words and run a FreqDist on it&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fdist&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nltk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FreqDist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modals&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;can&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;could&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;may&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;might&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;must&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;will&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;what&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;when&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;where&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;why&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;:&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fdist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grappling with this problem, Brandon re-introduced me to something I had learned about before but never had to use—object-oriented programming. Rather than performing a linear series of functions on my text file, reorganizing my code along OOP lines let me treat this text file as an object with many attributes, any of which I could access at any time. If I wanted my file (or object) as a giant list of words to perform a frequency distribution, I needed only to call upon that particular aspect (or attribute) of my object. If I then wanted Python to think of it as a tokenized list of lists I could just call on that particular attribute rather than having to send it through a series of transformations. It’s as if my ability to manipulate a file gained a third dimension— instead of begin stuck going from X to Y to Z and then back to X, I had access to all three stages of my file simultaneously. In essence, what was once a one-way data-type conveyor belt now became a fully-staffed NLP laboratory. In another pair programming session, we started to shift my more linear code to an object-oriented approach. What we came up with definitely needs refactoring (in my TODO list) and can certainly be improved (i.e., not overwriting a variable multiple times), but again, in the spirit of showing my learning process, I wanted to share a visual of this early version that marked my beginning to grapple with OOP for the first time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# attributes live here&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fn&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;raw_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get_raw_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tokenize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;processed_tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lowercase&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;processed_tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;no_punctuation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;processed_tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;no_spaces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally “getting” object-oriented programming conceptually was truly a programming awakening for me, even if my initial attempts need some improvement—it hadn’t really made sense as an approach until I was faced with the problems it helps address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have the poems in all their fiery intensity, as well as the beginnings of actually using sentiment analysis as another way of thinking through them. As it currently stands, Brandon and I have started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://textblob.readthedocs.io/en/dev/quickstart.html#sentiment-analysis&quot;&gt;TextBlob &lt;/a&gt;to perform some basic tasks—more on that soon. If you have any questions or want to follow along, my GitHub project repository can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/reedeth/feelings&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2017/11/30/first-steps-with-nlp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2017/11/30/first-steps-with-nlp.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Measured Unrest in the Poetry of the Black Arts Movement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/measured-unrest-in-the-poetry-of-the-black-arts-movement/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the graduate fellows at the Scholars’ Lab this year, I am working on a year-long digital project (that’s also a chapter of my dissertation) in collaboration with the folks at the SLab. To sum it up in a sentence, the project hopes to offer a proof-of-concept for performing sentiment analysis on some of the most politically and affectively charged poetry of the 20th century, that of the Black Arts Movement of the 1960s and 70s. Today I wanted to post a brief overview and introduction to what I’m working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some context, my research investigates theories of affect as they relate to race, class, and gender in American literature. I focus in particular upon the provocation and articulation of emotions like frustration, anger, and discontentment within recent US literary history as they relate to systemic injustice. An agitprop play that ends with shouts for workers to unite in class revolution; a poetic broadside that vents frustrations against white supremacy in America; a novel that indulges in a revenge fantasy against America’s colonial history. Unlike plays, poems, or novels that seem to obscure, submerge, or confound their own political dimensions, these works wear their hearts on their sleeves: they are frustrated, pissed off with how things are, and unafraid to speak truth to power in a direct, seemingly “un-literary” way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain level, then, this is a question of how, where, and to what ends aesthetics and politics meet in a work of literature. To offer a tidy narrative of this prickly history, this sensibility that mobilizes aesthetic objects to address political injustice has posed all kinds of unexpected, even contradictory problems for literary study. On the one hand, the cool detachment of aesthetic mediation keeps experimental works like John Dos Passos’s Communist-leaning &lt;em&gt;U.S.A.&lt;/em&gt; trilogy from being seen as mere propaganda, but runs the risk of appearing elitist or self-indulgent. On the other hand, the red-hot political outrage of a protest poem by Amiri Baraka or Sonia Sanchez grounds itself in the present, but may be attacked for subordinating aesthetic sophistication to political agendas. “Anger is loaded with information and energy,” says Audre Lorde in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blackpast.org/1981-audre-lorde-uses-anger-women-responding-racism&quot;&gt;a 1981 speech&lt;/a&gt; on its political uses—but the nature of this affective information, sparked by a given political present, becomes highly vexed when articulated by different groups through aesthetic objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on recent scholarship (like the work of Lauren Berlant and Sianne Ngai) suggesting that feeling gives structure to cultural formations, I argue that a history of unrest in America reveals a pattern of artistic response, a &lt;em&gt;sensibility&lt;/em&gt;, precipitated by specific historical moments but translated into aesthetic practice through a stable constellation of affective structures. To this end, I examine continuities between politically-engaged aesthetic projects from three periods of discontent in American history: radical journals like &lt;em&gt;Partisan Review&lt;/em&gt; in the 1930s; the revolutionary poetry of the Black Arts Movement in the 60s; and contemporary revenge-driven novels drawing from the Red Power movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My digital project as a graduate fellow is the second of those three chapters. In it I hope to ask two questions in particular: first, how are the feelings associated with injustice in the 1960s and 1970s coded in terms of race and gender? The Black Arts Movement first took shape at the height of the Black Power Movement with the foundation of the Revolutionary Theatre by Amiri Baraka in 1965. As Larry Neal—one of its principal theorists—says in a 1969 manifesto, the “Black Arts movement seeks to link, in a highly conscious manner, art and politics” toward “the liberation of Black people.” Moreover, the movement’s “black esthetic” is famous for its affective dimensions, often exploring the limits and political uses of anger, frustration, and poetic rage. But while BAM writers sought to link art and politics through explicitly racial terms, many—though by no means all—were marked by a failure to attend to the intersections of gender with racial injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to my second question: what can natural language processing techniques like sentiment analysis show us about the relations between different dimensions of poetry—like affect and gender—given that poetry, unlike movie reviews or customer feedback, is highly figurative and notoriously difficult to quantify in terms of sentiment or opinion? How can we combine the powerful scale of sentiment analysis with the granularity of close reading to explore the intersections of feeling, gender, race, and injustice in the radical poetry of this period? Moreover, by employing an interpretive method that is in part suspect from a revolutionary perspective—a distanced, potentially de-contextualized computational analysis—I wonder: what limits might these methods have in reading texts that are themselves shaped by the experience of an intense surveillance culture fearful of radical thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The already vibrant conversations on sentiment analysis and NLP more generally have been illuminating in forming my questions. The discussion between Matthew Jockers and Annie Swafford on the &lt;em&gt;Syuzhet&lt;/em&gt; package and “archetypal plot shapes” has helped me not only to explore the current &lt;a href=&quot;https://annieswafford.wordpress.com/category/syuzhet/&quot;&gt;possibilities and limitations&lt;/a&gt; of sentiment analysis as applied to literary corpora, but also to think through the kinds of results we expect from digital projects and how we verify those results as an academic community. With regards to poetry and NLP more specifically, Lisa Rhody’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-1/topic-modeling-and-figurative-language-by-lisa-m-rhody/&quot;&gt;topic modeling of highly figurative ekphrastic poetry&lt;/a&gt; is a great model for how unexpected failures in textual analysis can also be productive, prompting us towards new questions as well as new understandings of familiar methods like close reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I have been working in collaboration with folks at the Scholars’ Lab to work through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/book/&quot;&gt;the NLTK handbook&lt;/a&gt;, building and prepping my corpus, and beginning to implement some NLP techniques with &lt;a href=&quot;https://textblob.readthedocs.io/en/dev/&quot;&gt;TextBlob &lt;/a&gt;on what I have so far. Another post on those first forays into NLP and sentiment analysis coming soon! In the meantime, if you have any questions about the project, texts or tools I should check out, or just find it interesting and want to talk about it, send me an email! I’ll be posting about my progress over the course of the coming months and aiming to keep my process as open as possible to new ideas, feedback, and inspiration from unexpected places.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2017/11/15/measured-unrest.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2017/11/15/measured-unrest.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Ghost in the Graph: A Recap on Time, Things, and Entanglement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/the-ghost-in-the-graph-a-recap-on-time-things-and-entanglement/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab &lt;/a&gt; - this is the protein-rich version of a series of related posts from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;our Praxis site&lt;/a&gt;, with fresh reflections on the process and product now that I’m done. If you want to see originals, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/02/11-2-week-project-time-through-things/&quot;&gt;the project idea&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;the data itself as I recorded it&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;first attempt at a visualization&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;second attempt at a series of visualizatio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;ns&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time through things. This was the motivating idea behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/02/11-2-week-project-time-through-things/&quot;&gt;a week-long project &lt;/a&gt;I started at the beginning of November for Praxis. Everyone on the team decided to track, monitor, or experiment with lived time in one way or another for a full week. James looked at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/11/cloud-data/&quot;&gt;clouds&lt;/a&gt;; Lydia at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/10/31/music-tracking-update/&quot;&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;; Gillet at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/18/outside-time/&quot;&gt;time indoors and outdoors&lt;/a&gt;; Bremen at policing and affect; Rachel at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/f-bomb/&quot;&gt;language use&lt;/a&gt;. I chose to think about time through things. So I wrote down in a notebook &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;everything I used in a seven day period&lt;/a&gt;, from when I woke up to when I went to bed. Obviously what counts as “use” and what counts as a “thing” gets conceptually gritty very quickly. To stay sane, I took them in their most intuitive, ordinary senses, which means Yes, my methodology was in some ways arbitrary, but also Yes, I managed not to go nuts while seeing it through. So the data is not perfect, but it’s there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I want to do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a chance to look at my other posts this year related to Praxis’s current explorations of time and ways of representing it (&lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1021-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;When Things Break&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;Time Pieces&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;Three Sketches&lt;/a&gt; in particular) it becomes clear I’m interested in nonhuman and what some might call posthuman ways of thinking about time. For me, this means I’m thinking about the way time works for stuff, things, and entities that aren’t people. Which can be difficult because as humans we tend to anthropomorphize everything - humans think through human lenses. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iep.utm.edu/met-phen/#H4&quot;&gt;Jacques Derrida famously argued&lt;/a&gt; that Western philosophy itself is anthropomorphic (and ethnocentric) - others have &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/M/bo3637992.html&quot;&gt;argued related things in different venues&lt;/a&gt;. And these ideas make a lot of sense. If the human species were physically different (blind but great sense of smell; two brains per body; a strain of bacteria; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tralfamadore#Slaughterhouse-Five&quot;&gt;four-dimensional&lt;/a&gt;) our understandings of lots of things – basically everything – would be affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if it’s a difficult project, thinking of nonhuman and posthuman time also feels like an important project. For example, this kind of thinking might help us wrap our heads around our role in systems or entities bafflingly larger than us, like the geologic time of our planet and our power as a species to shape its geologic future. For a few of my favorite examples of this kind of thinking, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/hyperobjects&quot;&gt;Timothy Morton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/596640&quot;&gt;Dipesh Chakrabarty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;Bethany Nowviskie&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://salvage.zone/in-print/the-limits-of-utopia/&quot;&gt;China Miéville&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A less “planetary” example would be re-thinking how we as decision-making entities are influenced or “made to do” things by the non-human entities that surround us. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/20167474?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;Bruno Latour wonders&lt;/a&gt;: are you smoking the cigarette or does the cigarette smoke you? Well, as he says: both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how am I trying to think about posthuman or nonhuman time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this, let’s look at the data and what I did with it. My data, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;presented on the site&lt;/a&gt; in big blocks of words, almost looks like a kind of poetry (maybe &lt;a href=&quot;http://chronicle.com/article/Uncreative-Writing/128908/&quot;&gt;uncreative poetry&lt;/a&gt; in the vein of Kenneth Goldsmith). I took this strange data and did my best to represent it visually, both for practice with &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3 tools&lt;/a&gt; and also to eke more meaning out of what I’d done. For this visualization and the ones below, I’m posting images rather than the graphs themselves - if you want to play around with the sometimes sluggish originals, check out the links at the top of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my first attempted visualization, I borrowed from Jason Davies’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasondavies.com/parallel-sets/&quot;&gt;“Parallel Sets”&lt;/a&gt; visualization (with significant help from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wayne_graham&quot;&gt;Wayne&lt;/a&gt;). You can find here &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets&quot;&gt;the github page I took Davies’ code from originally&lt;/a&gt;, and his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets/blob/master/LICENSE&quot;&gt;license here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, I began with his beautiful graph and turned it quickly into an incomprehensible scribble. Behold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/12.3vis1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization 1&quot; width=&quot;934&quot; height=&quot;704&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a visualization of data, what I made is pretty close to nonsensical. And also unwieldy - the original doesn’t load right and can slow the page down significantly. This monstrosity didn’t come as a surprise to me, as I didn’t clean my data or prep it for what the code expected. I more or less just tried to crowbar my data into Davies’ code/setup until something came out the other end that looked anything remotely like a graph. So while I don’t know exactly what’s happening here, things &lt;em&gt;are &lt;/em&gt;happening. Some sort of nightmare causality is at work, even if only my laptop really knows what’s going on (or &lt;em&gt;not &lt;/em&gt;going on) as it tries to make sense of what I’m feeding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I take a step back, what it comes up with also feels kind of poetic, almost like the data itself. When you mouse over one of the catastrophic clusters and happen upon a single thread, the graph tries to produce a new narrative of objects for you. The pseudo-stories are wandering and garbled, but also charming and original. For example: “spoons -&amp;gt; mouse pad -&amp;gt; backpack -&amp;gt; chair -&amp;gt; yogurt -&amp;gt; metro card.” Or my personal favorite: “pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More useful, I think, are my &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;second round of visualizations&lt;/a&gt; . These are &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062045&quot;&gt;force-directed graphs&lt;/a&gt;, also from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3js.org&lt;/a&gt;, one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bost.ocks.org/mike/&quot;&gt;Mike Bostock’s many visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. As with Davies’ parallel sets graph, I used what Bostock had up on d3, replaced his data set with mine, and with a lot of help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt; figured out how to get it to read my .csv file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this method, I produced one force-directed graph for each day and a sprawling, magnificent mess at the end combining all seven days. In the graphs, each node (or point) represents a “thing” that I used. If you mouse over the node you can see which thing it represents. Every edge (or connecting line) represents a connection between those things – in this case, a connection between A and B means that A was used right after or right before B in my linear data. This means that the linearity, as well as the order of use, is collapsed in these representations. What we’re left with, however, is something new and potentially worth looking at on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different days have different shapes. Thursday’s things live in big billowing petals that loop out on long, solitary walks of minimal connection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/12.3vis2thursday.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization 2 Thursday&quot; width=&quot;934&quot; height=&quot;704&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday’s things live in much tighter, centralized clusters – most activity is shared activity, a miniature city of things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/12.3vis2sunday.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization 2 Sunday&quot; width=&quot;934&quot; height=&quot;704&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do these static, force-direct graphs of relationships between things have to do with time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YycAzdtUIko&quot;&gt;what I gather on the subject&lt;/a&gt;, modern physics has some counter-intuitive insights to offer regarding our ordinary bodily understanding of time, such that our intuited experience of it doesn’t necessarily correspond to how events happen in the nether realms of relativity. For example, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relativity_of_simultaneity&quot;&gt;the relativity of simultaneity&lt;/a&gt;, one observer might see A -&amp;gt; B -&amp;gt; C (with accurate measurements), while another with equal accuracy observes B -&amp;gt; C -&amp;gt; A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while orders of events may be muddled, the fact of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Causality_(physics)#Cause_and_effect_in_physics&quot;&gt;causality&lt;/a&gt; remains. So in one way of thinking, time for a person is less something that passes by moment to moment in a linear progression than it is a static line segment of every casually linked event, all existing simultaneously. In which case, static, simultaneous representations of multiple events might actually have an unusual kind of purchase when it comes to representing causal/temporal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happens when we try to think about this with regards to &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;? I’m thinking about causal relations between things that might not involve humans. For example, if humans were to disappear tomorrow (as in Weisman’s&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldwithoutus.com/index2.html&quot;&gt;The World Without Us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;), &lt;em&gt;things &lt;/em&gt;would very well continue to interact with one another. To expand on examples from my data: a pillow getting heavier, mustier, and moldier as moisture creeps into a dilapidating room, staining the sheets on which it rests, while both weigh down on a mattress whose metal springs start to rust and give (pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; mattress); freeze-thaw cycles crack and crumble sections of road until a telephone pole tips and snaps onto the hood of a parked convertible, sending glass onto the street (road -&amp;gt; pole -&amp;gt; car); and so on. Other writers have thought about this before: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1021-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt; I linked to Virginia Woolf’s depiction in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_the_Lighthouse&quot;&gt;To the Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;of a home left uninhabited for years. In Ray Bradbury’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_Will_Come_Soft_Rains_(short_story)&quot;&gt;“There Will Come Soft Rains”&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martian_Chronicles&quot;&gt;The Martian Chronicles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(not available as text online, but awesomely available as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LzhlU8rXgHc&quot;&gt;a recording read by Leonard Nimoy&lt;/a&gt;), we watch from a disembodied point of view as a futuristic home in California, long abandoned, slowly breaks down, from its automated kitchenware and mouse-Roombas to the automated poetry-reading voice in the bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Point being, things can very well interact with one another without humans. There may be no humans to perceive them and thus classify these encounters as between discrete, meaningful things, but from our current vantage we can at least imagine them. In this sense, these thing-graphs are speculative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there is a ghost in the graph – a body, my body, invisible save for traces left in having connected thing-nodes through use-edges. But in these graphs, the time that body spent making those connections evaporates, like steam from a cup of coffee. And what’s left is the cup of coffee itself - and all its associates. Though these associates were used in a specific linear order, I wanted instead to think of them as bound together causally, all entangled simultaneously within a given frame of reference (24 hours). Is this a chronology? Is it a timeline? A time network?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of observers arguing over linear orders-of-events, these things on this day have been strung together. A glass of water and a faucet, a toothbrush and toothpaste: somehow, someway, they were (are!) all tangled up with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I ever really think of “thing time” without using my very human body to think it through and write it all down? Of course not. The ghost is in the graph – the ghost (with a lot of help) put the graph online, is talking to you about the graph right now. But I can certainly try to imagine how we might think of these entanglements in less anthropomorphic ways, to de-center (in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor%E2%80%93network_theory&quot;&gt;the vein of Latour&lt;/a&gt;) the role of the human as sole prime agent, mover of all things. Rather, I have tried to show how these objects have lives of their own - and how, as active shaping forces, these lives are causally, temporally, entangled with ours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/12/03/ghost-in-the-graph.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/12/03/ghost-in-the-graph.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visualization #2 of Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with a significant amount of help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to get &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062045&quot;&gt;this force-directed graph&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3js.org&lt;/a&gt; up and running with my data set from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;“Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period”&lt;/a&gt;. This force-directed graph is one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bost.ocks.org/mike/&quot;&gt;Mike Bostock’s many graphs and visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. I used what he had up on d3, replaced his data set with mine, then with a ton of help from Eric figured out how to get it to read and represent my .csv file even though the original was primed to read a .json data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see below are a series of force-directed graphs. &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/james-p-ascher/&quot;&gt;James&lt;/a&gt; recently made a similar representation of his cloud data using one such graph, which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/cloud-data-present/i&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this post, I produced one force-directed graph for each day and a sprawling, magnificent mess at the end that combines all seven days. In these graphs, each node (or point) represents a “thing” that I used. If you hover over the node with your mouse you can see which thing it represents. Every edge or connecting line represents a connection between those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this representation, a connection between Thing A and Thing B means that Thing A was used right after or right before Thing B in my linear sequence of use as recorded in the data. This means that many aspects of my data were collapsed  in this particular representation. For example: if a thing was used more once in my original data, this does not appear on these graphs. The order of use is also completely gone. So a significant amount of context has been sheared off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we’re left with, however, is something new, and I hope worthwhile on it’s own. It is very different, and perhaps more interesting as a visualization of data, than  &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;my first “visualization”&lt;/a&gt; of this same dataset. Here you can start to see the way different days take different physical shapes in this graph, depending on the kinds of things use and their “connectedness” to other things in their network. For example, Thursday’s things (a day in which I took &lt;a href=&quot;http://nycshuttle.com/&quot;&gt;a bus&lt;/a&gt; from Charlottesville to NYC) live in big billowing petals of connection that loop out on their own for extended series of edges. On the other hand, Sunday, during which I took the same bus &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; to Charlottesville from NYC, lives in much tighter, centralized clusters with fewer strands of relative un-connectedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, more on what all this might mean later. Right now I’m still just practicing getting these things operational and embedded in a post on our site (in this case using &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Gist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/&quot;&gt;bl.ocks.org&lt;/a&gt;). I plan on writing a post reflecting on this whole process and synthesizing a bit, and maybe even one more visualization. We’ll see. Until then: the graphs themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/8259c3984ad826227c6d/&quot;&gt;Monday, 11.2.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/bf87d62d2c52e815a9ae/&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 11.3.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/18dedb74e52b69a8fbed/&quot;&gt;Wednesday, 11.4.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/7f8e0cb2446004ffe39c/&quot;&gt;Thursday, 11.5.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/577082f32ea974c76958/&quot;&gt;Friday, 11.6.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/97800a0d03021f0dc65a/&quot;&gt;Saturday, 11.7.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/d3b68c10128d46fb6f28/&quot;&gt;Sunday, 11.8.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/57868ff574651558813a/&quot;&gt;All seven days combined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 15:39:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/11/20/visualization-2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/11/20/visualization-2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visualization #1 of Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve tried a few different &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery&quot;&gt;visualization examples&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;the d3 site&lt;/a&gt;. They are amazing. The one I used here is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasondavies.com/parallel-sets/&quot;&gt;“Parallel Sets”&lt;/a&gt; and made by Jason Davies. You can find here &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets&quot;&gt;the github page that I took this code from originally&lt;/a&gt;, with his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets/blob/master/LICENSE&quot;&gt;license here&lt;/a&gt;. With a LOT of &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/wayne-graham/&quot;&gt;Wayne’s&lt;/a&gt; help I was able to get this thing operable with my data set, which can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/every&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but is really just a .csv file of my previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;“Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/28701d282419c7f37a25/&quot;&gt;here it is&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, in my capable hands Davies’ once beautiful graph has been promptly turned into an incomprehensible - though still, amazingly, interactive - scribble. As a visualization of data, it’s pretty close to nonsensical. This doesn’t come as a surprise to me, as I more or less just tried to crowbar my set of data into Davies’ code/setup until something came up that looked anything like his original graph. Which is does! Sort of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at Davies’ original visualization, it’s of survivors of the Titanic according to four dimensions: survived/perished, female/male, child/adult, second-class/first-class/third-class/crew. On the page he calls it “a visualization technique for multidimensional categorical data.” I don’t think I would describe, exactly, what I have here as “multidimensional categorical data.” But the graph keeps trying to read it as such. So when you hover over certain lines, it’s trying to give you a kind of multidimensional look at a given object, though because my .csv file is probably sloppy and things haven’t been connected right, what it ends up giving is … totally unclear. Some sort of causality is at work, but only my laptop really knows what’s going on (or &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, I actually find what it comes up with kind of poetic. When you mouse over a line (which is almost impossible for a lot of the lines because it’s all so tightly nested) the graph keeps trying to produce a wandering, garbled, yet charming narrative of objects. Maybe what gets me is that there’s a logic at work here, but only the site and my computer can understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; things are happening, things &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; happening - I get the results of this logic in the visualization, pseudo-stories like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;spoons -&amp;gt; mouse pad -&amp;gt; backpack -&amp;gt; chair -&amp;gt; yogurt -&amp;gt; metro card&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This combination that doesn’t show up in my writing at all, but when it comes out of the graph on its own it has a kind of personality to it (yogurt on the subway - a spoon-based mousepad?). Here’s a short, punchy, no-nonsense set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;iPhone -&amp;gt; stairs -&amp;gt; toothpaste&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my personal favorite:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whoever made this last one must have been so sleepy. It looks like something I would produce at the end of the day, mind drifting elsewhere, drowsy, hungry. Sheets, sheets, sheets!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention there’s this whole twilight zone of gray hollow graph on the right, representative of empty cells on my .csv file (some days had more “things used” than others) … &lt;a href=&quot;http://vignette1.wikia.nocookie.net/powerlisting/images/6/6d/Supermassive_black_hole.jpeg/revision/latest?cb=20121206160459&quot;&gt;maybe don’t go over there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of even trying to get this working, I think I want to try using another example from d3 just for the practice of it. Next is probably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mbostock.github.io/d3/talk/20111116/bundle.html&quot;&gt;hierarchical edge bundling example&lt;/a&gt;. Until then!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 14:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/21: When Things Break</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1021-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;on the Scholars’ Lab.]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third of my four installments (here’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; of Inktober). And oh boy, get ready for some strange-looking sketches in this one. I tried to use a new kind of pen that has two tips and can make way thicker marks, which has resulted in many many failed drawings and a few semi-successful ones. I present to you the semi-successful ones. (For those interested in drawing implements, I’ve been using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sakuraofamerica.com/pen-archival&quot;&gt;0.35mm Pigma Micron&lt;/a&gt; but this time tried out a &lt;a href=&quot;http://tombowusa.com/dual-brush-pen-602.html&quot;&gt;Tombow Dual Brush Pen, N15 black&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems I had with my tools this week, believe it or not, fits thematically with what I’ve been trying to draw: when things break. Or when things (tools) don’t work the way you want them to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with time? Let’s look at the first picture I’m sharing, a drawing of one of my shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.23samba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Samba&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;762&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably can’t tell from what I drew here, but this shoe is thrashed on the inside. The back heel has completely torn through the cloth and this bluish plastic is exposed. There’s also a split starting on the outer-toe area through the leather but I couldn’t really draw it that well. On a side note, looking so closely at my shoe for so long reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Ug3ArDMHLnQC&amp;amp;pg=PA540&amp;amp;lpg=PA540&amp;amp;dq=delillo+underworld+shoe+name+the+parts&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=fWnNKYyQUi&amp;amp;sig=KI5UxZA50WbPPs_DtATUDEeNygE&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAmoVChMI8N3n85_UyAIVRHY-Ch08OAK9#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=delillo%20underworld%20shoe%20name%20the%20parts&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;this scene from Don DeLillo’s &lt;em&gt;Underworld&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - from “Sometimes I think…” to the bottom of p. 543 - in which a boy is asked to name as many parts of a shoe as possible. I, in particular, had problems with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shoeguide.org/shoe_anatomy/&quot;&gt;the vamp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Point being, the shoe is beat, from toe cap to insole. It’s spent. Both of my shoes are. I’ve worn these &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adidas.com/us/samba-classic-shoes/034563.html&quot;&gt;sambas&lt;/a&gt; practically every day since I bought them and often play soccer in them. I will have to buy a new pair very soon. What’s interesting is the way in which I learn that they need to be replaced: I need to buy a new pair because the shoe, as a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt;, has “stopped working.” It’s a trigger of some kind that produces an almost automatic response: thing you need breaks? Time to get a new one! Normally, I don’t think about my shoes at all. They’re comfortable and easy to walk in, so they’re just kind of there - they’re “present at hand” (or “at foot”! Ha!). I know they exist, but I’m no more aware of them than I am of my feet, legs, or hips while walking around. That is, until something goes wrong - the felt wears out and chafes my heel; I start to get blisters; the bottom cushioning wears through; the shoe splits at a side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Heidegger, when a piece of equipment breaks or malfunctions &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#ModEnc&quot;&gt;it acquires a new kind of visibility&lt;/a&gt;, as though it were semi-transparent before while being used. (If you’re wondering what Heidegger is doing here or want more context, check out my &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; posts). Most importantly, this new visibility changes how and what the thing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; - the implication being that situational contexts actually change &lt;em&gt;what things are&lt;/em&gt; for us (Dasein) in the world. So when my shoe ‘breaks,’ it changes how it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in the everyday-ness of my world. It stops being a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polyvore.com/cgi/img-thing?.out=jpg&amp;amp;size=l&amp;amp;tid=71957156&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoe&lt;/em&gt; shoe&lt;/a&gt; and starts being a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.celia-pardini.fr/_/rsrc/1316020452111/my-destroyed-shoes/destroyShoes3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;trash&lt;/em&gt; shoe&lt;/a&gt;. Its time is up. In his 1935 essay &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger-aesthetics/#HeiForArtIntThrPilHeiUndArt&quot;&gt;“The Origin of the Work of Art,”&lt;/a&gt; Heidegger himself actually looks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://harpers.org/wp-content/uploads/van-gogh-a-pair-of-shoes.jpg&quot;&gt;a famous pair of shoes&lt;/a&gt; as an example of how an artistic representation of them can pull together and have the power to &lt;em&gt;disclose&lt;/em&gt; a kind of life-world despite simply being ‘equipment.’ And it seems to me that a totally trashed pair of shoes does this very differently than a pair fresh out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wonder: when a thing’s lifespan as a thing is over (a lifespan determined in large part by its use context: i.e. a pair of boots that sits in a closet all year vs. pair used by a carpenter or roofer on worksites almost every day), what kind of lifespan does it acquire as something broken? How does the life of a &lt;em&gt;trash&lt;/em&gt; shoe different from a &lt;em&gt;shoe&lt;/em&gt; shoe, assuming that it’s possible these two shoes might &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; different things for me? An illustrative example would be something like comparing how we think of the ‘lifespan’ of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carsofamericainc.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/iStock_000013970322XSmall.jpg&quot;&gt;car battery&lt;/a&gt; with the ‘lifespan’ of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fullcarservice.org/images/category/carblog/carnews/bat_last/car-battery1.jpg&quot;&gt;dead car battery&lt;/a&gt;: the first has to do with human use, the possibility of travel, cold winter mornings, brand reliability, maintenance, usually a matter of years; the latter with molecular half-lives, recycling practices, landfills, all on a much longer scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sketch with the new pen, this of an abandoned vehicle, engine- and battery-less. With some color! (If you want to see the original I was trying to draw, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;http://i.ytimg.com/vi/j2SGlkFfH3Y/maxresdefault.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.23carintheweeds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Car in the Weeds&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a kind of mythical image for me. In his song &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomwaits.com/songs/song/368/Bad_As_Me/&quot;&gt;“Bad As Me”&lt;/a&gt; Tom Waits calls it simply “the car in the weeds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So two main questions: on the one hand, how do we conceive of time passing for things that are ‘invisible’ and ‘present-at-hand’ - things that are there in the background almost all the time, but that we take for granted until lost or broken? And on the other, how do we conceive of time passing for things that are out of sight &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; mind - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/06/26-trillion-pounds-of-garbage-where-does-the-worlds-trash-go/258234/&quot;&gt;things that have been cast aside&lt;/a&gt;, like this car is now, or my shoe soon will be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more: a pencil with a broken tip, and a pencil that has been sharpened way past its point of practical usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.23pencil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Broken Pencil&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;722&quot; /&gt;``&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when things break, when their ‘time is up,’ they acquire a certain kind of urgency. They come to the fore. It’s almost like they come back into existence from some kind of constantly humming background noise. All of the sudden you have to decide what to do with this thing - do you fix it? Replace it with something else? Replace it with a new version of itself? Leave it in the weeds (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Pacific_garbage_patch&quot;&gt;or the center of the Pacific&lt;/a&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions may feel simple, or perhaps too straightforward, but they are the kinds of questions that matter for Daisen (us, humans, beings for whom being is a question) when it comes to things in our world. And because they matter to us in this way, these questions matter for how these objects &lt;em&gt;are &lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;are not&lt;/em&gt; in our worlds - and by world I mean the highly contingent world with which a given person is familiar and in which they live their day-to-day lives, one that is changing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminds me of another scene from another 20th century novel, the “Time Passes” section of Virginia Woolf’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_the_Lighthouse&quot;&gt;To the Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (much of which you can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=ng0Tg0FhRggC&amp;amp;q=time+passes#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=time%20passes&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;here on Google Books&lt;/a&gt;). Describing a home left more-or-less uninhabited for years, she writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;So with the house empty and the doors locked and the mattresses rolled round, those stray airs, advance guards of great armies, blustered in, brushed bare boards, nibbled and fanned, met nothing in bedroom or drawing-room that wholly resisted them but only hangings that flapped, wood that creaked, the bare legs of tables, saucepans and china already furred, tarnished, cracked. What people had shed and left - a pair of shoes, a shooting cap, some faded skirts and coats in wardrobes - those alone kept the human shape and in the emptiness indicated how once they were filled and animated; how once hands were busy with hooks and buttons; how once the looking-glass had held a face; had held a world hollowed out in which a figure turned, a hand flashed, the door opened, in came children rushing and tumbling; and went out again. … Loveliness and stillness clasped hands in the bedroom, and among the shrouded jugs and sheeted chairs even the prying of the wind, and the soft nose of the clammy sea airs, rubbing, snuffing, iterating, and reiterating their questions - “Will you fade? Will you perish?” - scarcely disturbed the peace, the indifference, the air of pure integrity, as if the question they asked scarcely needed that they should answer: we remain.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think more on just how my busted shoe, the car in the weeds, and the too-short pencil go about ‘remaining’ in the world, and how this might differ from their still-in-use counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 13:47:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/13: Time Pieces and Graphs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;on the Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello all - three more images for Inktober.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a continuation from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;my previous Inktober post&lt;/a&gt;, very simply, two tubes of toothpaste, both almost empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.13toothpaste.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Toothpaste&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was still thinking of the consumption of objects, for two reasons: first, because of their importance to a historical thinker deeply interested in time (and on my orals list), one Karl Marx, who writes on everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch10.htm&quot;&gt;the length of the working day&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch01.htm#S1&quot;&gt;labour-time itself here in the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And second, because a lot of people use toothpaste in their everyday life. It is something they consume very slowly, and often even forget that they have or that it’s running out; they measure out its consumption bit by bit over the course of many weeks, but its presence over time is ‘at hand,’ or taken for granted in a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start with Marx though, in the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt; (titled: Commodities) he defines the value of a commodity as “the labour time socially necessary for its production.” He then goes on to quote himself from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1844/manuscripts/preface.htm&quot;&gt;Economic &amp;amp; Philosophic Manuscripts of 1844&lt;/a&gt; saying that “As exchange values, all commodities are merely definite quantities of &lt;em&gt;congealed labour-time&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a phrase! &lt;em&gt;Congealed labour-time&lt;/em&gt;. As though the object in hand were physically made up of hours from the lives of others. The idea that an hour of life itself can be estranged from an individual and sold for monetary compensation, and that these hours of others then congeal into an object which sits on my bathroom sink for a set number of weeks is fascinating, and which Marx thinks through seriously, though too much to talk about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second point though, that people use toothpaste everyday, has to do with the thinking of another philosopher I’ve been reading while studying for my oral exams - &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/&quot;&gt;Martin Heidegger&lt;/a&gt;. Though he’s interested &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#BeiTim&quot;&gt;in his big work&lt;/a&gt; with ontological questions (like, what kind of being does the number 1 have vs. the color brown, a chair, the solar system, a historical event, my cat, etc) he also believes that things ‘are’ for humans (or &lt;em&gt;Dasein&lt;/em&gt; in his terminology, the being for whom being is an issue or question) in a way that is more natural. In his thinking, when I see a desk, I don’t go for some abstract, philosophical, Aristotelian route and think of it as a substance with attributes (such as squareness or brownness), I think more of whether or not it is the right size, or close enough to a reading light, or if it is an heirloom that needs to be treated carefully. That these considerations actually make up, in many ways, the ‘being’ of the table itself for Dasein (humans) was fascinating to me when I first started reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence: toothpaste! I brush my teeth twice a day and use toothpaste from a tube that looks like one of these. It is something that fits in my hand and I can tell how much time I have left with this particular tube just by picking it up. Using a brand new tube is very different from the ones I have drawn here, crumpling up tubes to try to make them last, to &lt;em&gt;extend their lives&lt;/em&gt;. The “time” of a tube of toothpaste, its lifespan, is relatively slow (or long) compared to, say, a quart of milk or loaf of bread. The same tube persists through many weeks of use, and there is even a certain feeling of ‘letting go’ and beginning again when I have to stop crushing up an old familiar tube and go buy new. And trying a new brand, flavor, or type of toothpaste is a strangely serious time commitment, a decision that persists in your everyday experience (and teeth) for weeks or months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connects with another picture, those of time pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.13laptopwatchphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Time Pieces&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to draw the things I look at during the day to tell what time it is. When this Dasein thinks of time (me), he probably thinks first of where he looks to ‘tell the time,’ the things I use to make sure that I am not late, or that I am getting enough sleep, or that I remember to eat lunch. For me these are my computer and my phone. My window into Greenwich Mean Time is almost always small numbers on a screen that sometimes fail to update to Daylight Savings. A lot of people have watches though, so I wanted to draw one of them too. I wonder how these objects of mediators of this standard time influence how time actually feels for the humans who use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is more abstract. I was thinking of Johanna Drucker’s work in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674724938&quot;&gt;Graphesis: Visual Forms of Knowledge Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and particularly an article she wrote for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/&quot;&gt;DHQ&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html&quot;&gt;“Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display”&lt;/a&gt; in which she gives some examples of how humanists can use graphical representations. So I decided to draw some graphs about how we might experience time in a 24-hour period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.13graphs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graphs&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was envisioning that a given person would travel along the path of the line, x-axis being each hour passing, and y-axis being… something else. Experience? Not sure - point being, although the same number of ‘hours’ passed for each line, the length, trajectory, and experience of each line (or sets of lines) was very unique. Would love to draw some more of these, or at least think through them a little more seriously before the month is out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 13:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/5: Three Sketches</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;on the Scholars’ Lab.]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanted to put up a few time sketches for our own version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mrjakeparker.com/inktober&quot;&gt;Inktober&lt;/a&gt;. I’m aiming for every other day or so, so here’s three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three have to do with time and consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.5.movietime.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Popcorn&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love going to the movies, and usually opt for the biggest popcorn possible (bucket) but wonder how differently and quickly the ‘time of eating’ passes depending on how big your eating vessel is (I’m sure plenty of others have written about this - just Googling around quickly I found an entire website dedicated to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smallplatemovement.org/&quot;&gt;using smaller plates&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.5pintbythehour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pints&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one is another thing some people do to pass time together - having a drink at a bar or restaurant, which can go slow or fast. Here I tried to draw the rings that beer leaves behind as a marker of how much time passed where for the beer in this particular glass. Beer time! Reminds me of &lt;a href=&quot;http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Slughorn&#39;s_Hourglass&quot;&gt;Slughorn’s Hourglass&lt;/a&gt; in Harry Potter, which goes faster or slower depending on the quality of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.5cigarettebreak.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cigarettes&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is a cigarette - read a poem for orals by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/sherman-alexie&quot;&gt;Sherman Alexie &lt;/a&gt;with James Dean in it (called “Tourists”), got me thinking of the images of Dean &lt;a href=&quot;http://images.amcnetworks.com/blogs.amctv.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/2jacket.jpg&quot;&gt;with a cigarette in his red jacket&lt;/a&gt; (no color in that photo, but pretty sure that’s the jacket) and got thinking of how so many people frame “breaks” from their day, little slices of time, around something like cigarette “breaks.” As though they were carrying a pack of minutes in their pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 13:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time and Praxis 2015-2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Time is a massive concept. If you were asked to think about it – how it works, feels, changes, what it looks like, how people go about talking about it, or representing it – where would you start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a person interested and invested in critical theory, my initial reflex would be to go to philosophers, phenomenologists – writers like &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#TemTem&quot;&gt;Martin Heidegger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/merleau-ponty/&quot;&gt;Maurice Merleau-Ponty&lt;/a&gt;, and so on. Or check in with narrative theorists, think again about what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%A9rard_Genette#Order&quot;&gt;Gérard Genette&lt;/a&gt; says about time and narrative in &lt;em&gt;Narrative Discourse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second reflex would be to look at art and cultural objects. I’ve been trying to watch and/or reconsider as many time-travel movies as I had time for, everything from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4CC60HJvZRE&quot;&gt;Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8wqVHjK2bQs&quot;&gt;Donnie Darko&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;to something more straightforward like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c4Jo8QoOTQ4&quot;&gt;The Terminator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes you find something unexpected – for example, trying to &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/657/&quot;&gt;untangle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Primer &lt;/em&gt;after watching it last week, Gillet (a fellow Praxis member) commented that manipulating time in films can have a certain scare-factor, almost like it’s a specific branch of horror movies. I’d never thought about it that way before. Time, and the manipulation of time, has the power to frighten us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, games: like &lt;a href=&quot;http://braid-game.com/&quot;&gt;Braid&lt;/a&gt;, where manipulating time is the only way to solve puzzles and progress through the narrative. Or (at Jeremy’s suggestion) checking out Ian Bogost’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://bogost.com/games/aslowyear/&quot;&gt;A Slow Year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, literature. I thought first to a classics like H.G. Wells’ 1895 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Time_Machine&quot;&gt;The Time Machine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;or Ray Bradbury’s 1952 short story &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Sound_of_Thunder&quot;&gt;“A Sound of Thunder,”&lt;/a&gt; where tourist big-game hunters go back in time to kill dinosaurs, but (spoilers) someone accidentally steps on a butterfly and changes the whole course of history. Then to Kurt Vonnegut’s 1969 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slaughterhouse-Five&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse Five &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(probably because it’s the first book I ever wrote a book report on), where a character becomes “unstuck in time” as he dips in and out of his life experiences. Or even to something like Ruth Ozeki’s 2013 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ruthozeki.com/writing-film/a-tale-for-the-time-being/&quot;&gt;A Tale for the Time Being&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(which I’m reading for my oral exams)&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;where relationships with past and present “time beings” might, in some ways, influence one another, even when those cross-temporal relationships are mediated textually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many movies, games, novels, short stories, poems, and plays I could go to here it’s nuts – not even looking at works with entangled narrative structures like the film &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0209144/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memento&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;or Faulkner’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Absalom,_Absalom!&quot;&gt;Absalom, Absalom!&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(for example). These above are just the first that come to mind, each of which interacts with time and experiences time a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first time writing here as a Praxis Fellow for the 2015-2016 year. Along with &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/charter-2015-2016/&quot;&gt;producing a charter&lt;/a&gt;, this year we’re all trying to think about &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; in as many different ways as possible, staying wide open with it and willing to explore any new possibilities, each coming at it from our own unique angle. Throughout the year, in our work and in posts like this, I’ll try to keep track of and share what I feel like I am able to bring to our work from my own unique perspective (apparently even if sometimes that means just talking about a bunch of time-travel stories I’m excited about). We’re only a few weeks in, and I can already say how excited I am to be working with the Praxis team and all the folks at the Scholars’ Lab this coming year. I can’t wait to see what we come up with!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/09/24/praxis_and_time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/09/24/praxis_and_time.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
