<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethan Reed</title>
    <description>Personal blog of Ethan Reed, PhD Candidate in English Literature at the University of Virginia.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 11:14:31 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 11:14:31 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Ghost in the Graph: A Recap on Time, Things, and Entanglement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/the-ghost-in-the-graph-a-recap-on-time-things-and-entanglement/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab &lt;/a&gt; - this is the protein-rich version of a series of related posts from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;our Praxis site&lt;/a&gt;, with fresh reflections on the process and product now that I’m done. If you want to see originals, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/02/11-2-week-project-time-through-things/&quot;&gt;the project idea&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;the data itself as I recorded it&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;first attempt at a visualization&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;second attempt at a series of visualizatio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;ns&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time through things. This was the motivating idea behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/02/11-2-week-project-time-through-things/&quot;&gt;a week-long project &lt;/a&gt;I started at the beginning of November for Praxis. Everyone on the team decided to track, monitor, or experiment with lived time in one way or another for a full week. James looked at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/11/cloud-data/&quot;&gt;clouds&lt;/a&gt;; Lydia at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/10/31/music-tracking-update/&quot;&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;; Gillet at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/memo/2015/11/18/outside-time/&quot;&gt;time indoors and outdoors&lt;/a&gt;; Bremen at policing and affect; Rachel at &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/f-bomb/&quot;&gt;language use&lt;/a&gt;. I chose to think about time through things. So I wrote down in a notebook &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;everything I used in a seven day period&lt;/a&gt;, from when I woke up to when I went to bed. Obviously what counts as “use” and what counts as a “thing” gets conceptually gritty very quickly. To stay sane, I took them in their most intuitive, ordinary senses, which means Yes, my methodology was in some ways arbitrary, but also Yes, I managed not to go nuts while seeing it through. So the data is not perfect, but it’s there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I want to do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a chance to look at my other posts this year related to Praxis’s current explorations of time and ways of representing it (&lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1021-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;When Things Break&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;Time Pieces&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;Three Sketches&lt;/a&gt; in particular) it becomes clear I’m interested in nonhuman and what some might call posthuman ways of thinking about time. For me, this means I’m thinking about the way time works for stuff, things, and entities that aren’t people. Which can be difficult because as humans we tend to anthropomorphize everything - humans think through human lenses. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iep.utm.edu/met-phen/#H4&quot;&gt;Jacques Derrida famously argued&lt;/a&gt; that Western philosophy itself is anthropomorphic (and ethnocentric) - others have &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/M/bo3637992.html&quot;&gt;argued related things in different venues&lt;/a&gt;. And these ideas make a lot of sense. If the human species were physically different (blind but great sense of smell; two brains per body; a strain of bacteria; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tralfamadore#Slaughterhouse-Five&quot;&gt;four-dimensional&lt;/a&gt;) our understandings of lots of things – basically everything – would be affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if it’s a difficult project, thinking of nonhuman and posthuman time also feels like an important project. For example, this kind of thinking might help us wrap our heads around our role in systems or entities bafflingly larger than us, like the geologic time of our planet and our power as a species to shape its geologic future. For a few of my favorite examples of this kind of thinking, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/hyperobjects&quot;&gt;Timothy Morton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/596640&quot;&gt;Dipesh Chakrabarty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;Bethany Nowviskie&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://salvage.zone/in-print/the-limits-of-utopia/&quot;&gt;China Miéville&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A less “planetary” example would be re-thinking how we as decision-making entities are influenced or “made to do” things by the non-human entities that surround us. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/20167474?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;Bruno Latour wonders&lt;/a&gt;: are you smoking the cigarette or does the cigarette smoke you? Well, as he says: both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how am I trying to think about posthuman or nonhuman time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this, let’s look at the data and what I did with it. My data, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;presented on the site&lt;/a&gt; in big blocks of words, almost looks like a kind of poetry (maybe &lt;a href=&quot;http://chronicle.com/article/Uncreative-Writing/128908/&quot;&gt;uncreative poetry&lt;/a&gt; in the vein of Kenneth Goldsmith). I took this strange data and did my best to represent it visually, both for practice with &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3 tools&lt;/a&gt; and also to eke more meaning out of what I’d done. For this visualization and the ones below, I’m posting images rather than the graphs themselves - if you want to play around with the sometimes sluggish originals, check out the links at the top of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my first attempted visualization, I borrowed from Jason Davies’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasondavies.com/parallel-sets/&quot;&gt;“Parallel Sets”&lt;/a&gt; visualization (with significant help from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wayne_graham&quot;&gt;Wayne&lt;/a&gt;). You can find here &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets&quot;&gt;the github page I took Davies’ code from originally&lt;/a&gt;, and his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets/blob/master/LICENSE&quot;&gt;license here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, I began with his beautiful graph and turned it quickly into an incomprehensible scribble. Behold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/12.3vis1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization 1&quot; width=&quot;934&quot; height=&quot;704&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a visualization of data, what I made is pretty close to nonsensical. And also unwieldy - the original doesn’t load right and can slow the page down significantly. This monstrosity didn’t come as a surprise to me, as I didn’t clean my data or prep it for what the code expected. I more or less just tried to crowbar my data into Davies’ code/setup until something came out the other end that looked anything remotely like a graph. So while I don’t know exactly what’s happening here, things &lt;em&gt;are &lt;/em&gt;happening. Some sort of nightmare causality is at work, even if only my laptop really knows what’s going on (or &lt;em&gt;not &lt;/em&gt;going on) as it tries to make sense of what I’m feeding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I take a step back, what it comes up with also feels kind of poetic, almost like the data itself. When you mouse over one of the catastrophic clusters and happen upon a single thread, the graph tries to produce a new narrative of objects for you. The pseudo-stories are wandering and garbled, but also charming and original. For example: “spoons -&amp;gt; mouse pad -&amp;gt; backpack -&amp;gt; chair -&amp;gt; yogurt -&amp;gt; metro card.” Or my personal favorite: “pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More useful, I think, are my &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;second round of visualizations&lt;/a&gt; . These are &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062045&quot;&gt;force-directed graphs&lt;/a&gt;, also from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3js.org&lt;/a&gt;, one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bost.ocks.org/mike/&quot;&gt;Mike Bostock’s many visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. As with Davies’ parallel sets graph, I used what Bostock had up on d3, replaced his data set with mine, and with a lot of help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt; figured out how to get it to read my .csv file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this method, I produced one force-directed graph for each day and a sprawling, magnificent mess at the end combining all seven days. In the graphs, each node (or point) represents a “thing” that I used. If you mouse over the node you can see which thing it represents. Every edge (or connecting line) represents a connection between those things – in this case, a connection between A and B means that A was used right after or right before B in my linear data. This means that the linearity, as well as the order of use, is collapsed in these representations. What we’re left with, however, is something new and potentially worth looking at on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different days have different shapes. Thursday’s things live in big billowing petals that loop out on long, solitary walks of minimal connection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/12.3vis2thursday.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization 2 Thursday&quot; width=&quot;934&quot; height=&quot;704&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday’s things live in much tighter, centralized clusters – most activity is shared activity, a miniature city of things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/12.3vis2sunday.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization 2 Sunday&quot; width=&quot;934&quot; height=&quot;704&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do these static, force-direct graphs of relationships between things have to do with time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YycAzdtUIko&quot;&gt;what I gather on the subject&lt;/a&gt;, modern physics has some counter-intuitive insights to offer regarding our ordinary bodily understanding of time, such that our intuited experience of it doesn’t necessarily correspond to how events happen in the nether realms of relativity. For example, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relativity_of_simultaneity&quot;&gt;the relativity of simultaneity&lt;/a&gt;, one observer might see A -&amp;gt; B -&amp;gt; C (with accurate measurements), while another with equal accuracy observes B -&amp;gt; C -&amp;gt; A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while orders of events may be muddled, the fact of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Causality_(physics)#Cause_and_effect_in_physics&quot;&gt;causality&lt;/a&gt; remains. So in one way of thinking, time for a person is less something that passes by moment to moment in a linear progression than it is a static line segment of every casually linked event, all existing simultaneously. In which case, static, simultaneous representations of multiple events might actually have an unusual kind of purchase when it comes to representing causal/temporal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happens when we try to think about this with regards to &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;? I’m thinking about causal relations between things that might not involve humans. For example, if humans were to disappear tomorrow (as in Weisman’s&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldwithoutus.com/index2.html&quot;&gt;The World Without Us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;), &lt;em&gt;things &lt;/em&gt;would very well continue to interact with one another. To expand on examples from my data: a pillow getting heavier, mustier, and moldier as moisture creeps into a dilapidating room, staining the sheets on which it rests, while both weigh down on a mattress whose metal springs start to rust and give (pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; mattress); freeze-thaw cycles crack and crumble sections of road until a telephone pole tips and snaps onto the hood of a parked convertible, sending glass onto the street (road -&amp;gt; pole -&amp;gt; car); and so on. Other writers have thought about this before: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1021-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt; I linked to Virginia Woolf’s depiction in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_the_Lighthouse&quot;&gt;To the Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;of a home left uninhabited for years. In Ray Bradbury’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_Will_Come_Soft_Rains_(short_story)&quot;&gt;“There Will Come Soft Rains”&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martian_Chronicles&quot;&gt;The Martian Chronicles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(not available as text online, but awesomely available as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LzhlU8rXgHc&quot;&gt;a recording read by Leonard Nimoy&lt;/a&gt;), we watch from a disembodied point of view as a futuristic home in California, long abandoned, slowly breaks down, from its automated kitchenware and mouse-Roombas to the automated poetry-reading voice in the bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Point being, things can very well interact with one another without humans. There may be no humans to perceive them and thus classify these encounters as between discrete, meaningful things, but from our current vantage we can at least imagine them. In this sense, these thing-graphs are speculative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there is a ghost in the graph – a body, my body, invisible save for traces left in having connected thing-nodes through use-edges. But in these graphs, the time that body spent making those connections evaporates, like steam from a cup of coffee. And what’s left is the cup of coffee itself - and all its associates. Though these associates were used in a specific linear order, I wanted instead to think of them as bound together causally, all entangled simultaneously within a given frame of reference (24 hours). Is this a chronology? Is it a timeline? A time network?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of observers arguing over linear orders-of-events, these things on this day have been strung together. A glass of water and a faucet, a toothbrush and toothpaste: somehow, someway, they were (are!) all tangled up with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I ever really think of “thing time” without using my very human body to think it through and write it all down? Of course not. The ghost is in the graph – the ghost (with a lot of help) put the graph online, is talking to you about the graph right now. But I can certainly try to imagine how we might think of these entanglements in less anthropomorphic ways, to de-center (in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor%E2%80%93network_theory&quot;&gt;the vein of Latour&lt;/a&gt;) the role of the human as sole prime agent, mover of all things. Rather, I have tried to show how these objects have lives of their own - and how, as active shaping forces, these lives are causally, temporally, entangled with ours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/12/03/ghost-in-the-graph.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/12/03/ghost-in-the-graph.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visualization #2 of Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/20/visualization--2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with a significant amount of help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to get &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062045&quot;&gt;this force-directed graph&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3js.org&lt;/a&gt; up and running with my data set from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;“Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period”&lt;/a&gt;. This force-directed graph is one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bost.ocks.org/mike/&quot;&gt;Mike Bostock’s many graphs and visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. I used what he had up on d3, replaced his data set with mine, then with a ton of help from Eric figured out how to get it to read and represent my .csv file even though the original was primed to read a .json data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see below are a series of force-directed graphs. &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/james-p-ascher/&quot;&gt;James&lt;/a&gt; recently made a similar representation of his cloud data using one such graph, which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/cloud-data-present/i&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this post, I produced one force-directed graph for each day and a sprawling, magnificent mess at the end that combines all seven days. In these graphs, each node (or point) represents a “thing” that I used. If you hover over the node with your mouse you can see which thing it represents. Every edge or connecting line represents a connection between those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this representation, a connection between Thing A and Thing B means that Thing A was used right after or right before Thing B in my linear sequence of use as recorded in the data. This means that many aspects of my data were collapsed  in this particular representation. For example: if a thing was used more once in my original data, this does not appear on these graphs. The order of use is also completely gone. So a significant amount of context has been sheared off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we’re left with, however, is something new, and I hope worthwhile on it’s own. It is very different, and perhaps more interesting as a visualization of data, than  &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;my first “visualization”&lt;/a&gt; of this same dataset. Here you can start to see the way different days take different physical shapes in this graph, depending on the kinds of things use and their “connectedness” to other things in their network. For example, Thursday’s things (a day in which I took &lt;a href=&quot;http://nycshuttle.com/&quot;&gt;a bus&lt;/a&gt; from Charlottesville to NYC) live in big billowing petals of connection that loop out on their own for extended series of edges. On the other hand, Sunday, during which I took the same bus &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; to Charlottesville from NYC, lives in much tighter, centralized clusters with fewer strands of relative un-connectedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, more on what all this might mean later. Right now I’m still just practicing getting these things operational and embedded in a post on our site (in this case using &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Gist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/&quot;&gt;bl.ocks.org&lt;/a&gt;). I plan on writing a post reflecting on this whole process and synthesizing a bit, and maybe even one more visualization. We’ll see. Until then: the graphs themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday, 11.2.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/8259c3984ad826227c6d/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, 11.3.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/bf87d62d2c52e815a9ae/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, 11.4.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/18dedb74e52b69a8fbed/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday, 11.5.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/7f8e0cb2446004ffe39c/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, 11.6.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/577082f32ea974c76958/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 11.7.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/97800a0d03021f0dc65a/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday, 11.8.2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/d3b68c10128d46fb6f28/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All seven days combined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/57868ff574651558813a/&quot; width=&quot;2100px&quot; height=&quot;1650px&quot; /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 15:39:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/11/20/visualization-2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/11/20/visualization-2-of-everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visualization #1 of Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve tried a few different &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery&quot;&gt;visualization examples&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;the d3 site&lt;/a&gt;. They are amazing. The one I used here is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasondavies.com/parallel-sets/&quot;&gt;“Parallel Sets”&lt;/a&gt; and made by Jason Davies. You can find here &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets&quot;&gt;the github page that I took this code from originally&lt;/a&gt;, with his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets/blob/master/LICENSE&quot;&gt;license here&lt;/a&gt;. With a LOT of &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/wayne-graham/&quot;&gt;Wayne’s&lt;/a&gt; help I was able to get this thing operable with my data set, which can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/every&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but is really just a .csv file of my previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/11/12/everything-i-used-in-a-seven-day-period/&quot;&gt;“Everything I Used in a Seven Day Period”&lt;/a&gt;. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/reedeth/raw/28701d282419c7f37a25/&quot; width=&quot;1100px&quot; height=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, in my capable hands Davies’ once beautiful graph has been promptly turned into an incomprehensible - though still, amazingly, interactive - scribble. As a visualization of data, it’s pretty close to nonsensical. This doesn’t come as a surprise to me, as I more or less just tried to crowbar my set of data into Davies’ code/setup until something came up that looked anything like his original graph. Which is does! Sort of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at Davies’ original visualization, it’s of survivors of the Titanic according to four dimensions: survived/perished, female/male, child/adult, second-class/first-class/third-class/crew. On the page he calls it “a visualization technique for multidimensional categorical data.” I don’t think I would describe, exactly, what I have here as “multidimensional categorical data.” But the graph keeps trying to read it as such. So when you hover over certain lines, it’s trying to give you a kind of multidimensional look at a given object, though because my .csv file is probably sloppy and things haven’t been connected right, what it ends up giving is … totally unclear. Some sort of causality is at work, but only my laptop really knows what’s going on (or &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, I actually find what it comes up with kind of poetic. When you mouse over a line (which is almost impossible for a lot of the lines because it’s all so tightly nested) the graph keeps trying to produce a wandering, garbled, yet charming narrative of objects. Maybe what gets me is that there’s a logic at work here, but only the site and my computer can understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; things are happening, things &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; happening - I get the results of this logic in the visualization, pseudo-stories like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;spoons -&amp;gt; mouse pad -&amp;gt; backpack -&amp;gt; chair -&amp;gt; yogurt -&amp;gt; metro card&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This combination that doesn’t show up in my writing at all, but when it comes out of the graph on its own it has a kind of personality to it (yogurt on the subway - a spoon-based mousepad?). Here’s a short, punchy, no-nonsense set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;iPhone -&amp;gt; stairs -&amp;gt; toothpaste&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my personal favorite:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pillow -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets -&amp;gt; sheets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whoever made this last one must have been so sleepy. It looks like something I would produce at the end of the day, mind drifting elsewhere, drowsy, hungry. Sheets, sheets, sheets!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention there’s this whole twilight zone of gray hollow graph on the right, representative of empty cells on my .csv file (some days had more “things used” than others) … &lt;a href=&quot;http://vignette1.wikia.nocookie.net/powerlisting/images/6/6d/Supermassive_black_hole.jpeg/revision/latest?cb=20121206160459&quot;&gt;maybe don’t go over there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of even trying to get this working, I think I want to try using another example from d3 just for the practice of it. Next is probably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mbostock.github.io/d3/talk/20111116/bundle.html&quot;&gt;hierarchical edge bundling example&lt;/a&gt;. Until then!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 14:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/11/18/visualizing-everything-i-used.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/21: When Things Break</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1021-when-things-break/&quot;&gt;on the Scholars’ Lab.]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third of my four installments (here’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; of Inktober). And oh boy, get ready for some strange-looking sketches in this one. I tried to use a new kind of pen that has two tips and can make way thicker marks, which has resulted in many many failed drawings and a few semi-successful ones. I present to you the semi-successful ones. (For those interested in drawing implements, I’ve been using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sakuraofamerica.com/pen-archival&quot;&gt;0.35mm Pigma Micron&lt;/a&gt; but this time tried out a &lt;a href=&quot;http://tombowusa.com/dual-brush-pen-602.html&quot;&gt;Tombow Dual Brush Pen, N15 black&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems I had with my tools this week, believe it or not, fits thematically with what I’ve been trying to draw: when things break. Or when things (tools) don’t work the way you want them to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with time? Let’s look at the first picture I’m sharing, a drawing of one of my shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.23samba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Samba&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;762&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably can’t tell from what I drew here, but this shoe is thrashed on the inside. The back heel has completely torn through the cloth and this bluish plastic is exposed. There’s also a split starting on the outer-toe area through the leather but I couldn’t really draw it that well. On a side note, looking so closely at my shoe for so long reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Ug3ArDMHLnQC&amp;amp;pg=PA540&amp;amp;lpg=PA540&amp;amp;dq=delillo+underworld+shoe+name+the+parts&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=fWnNKYyQUi&amp;amp;sig=KI5UxZA50WbPPs_DtATUDEeNygE&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAmoVChMI8N3n85_UyAIVRHY-Ch08OAK9#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=delillo%20underworld%20shoe%20name%20the%20parts&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;this scene from Don DeLillo’s &lt;em&gt;Underworld&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - from “Sometimes I think…” to the bottom of p. 543 - in which a boy is asked to name as many parts of a shoe as possible. I, in particular, had problems with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shoeguide.org/shoe_anatomy/&quot;&gt;the vamp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Point being, the shoe is beat, from toe cap to insole. It’s spent. Both of my shoes are. I’ve worn these &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adidas.com/us/samba-classic-shoes/034563.html&quot;&gt;sambas&lt;/a&gt; practically every day since I bought them and often play soccer in them. I will have to buy a new pair very soon. What’s interesting is the way in which I learn that they need to be replaced: I need to buy a new pair because the shoe, as a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt;, has “stopped working.” It’s a trigger of some kind that produces an almost automatic response: thing you need breaks? Time to get a new one! Normally, I don’t think about my shoes at all. They’re comfortable and easy to walk in, so they’re just kind of there - they’re “present at hand” (or “at foot”! Ha!). I know they exist, but I’m no more aware of them than I am of my feet, legs, or hips while walking around. That is, until something goes wrong - the felt wears out and chafes my heel; I start to get blisters; the bottom cushioning wears through; the shoe splits at a side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Heidegger, when a piece of equipment breaks or malfunctions &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#ModEnc&quot;&gt;it acquires a new kind of visibility&lt;/a&gt;, as though it were semi-transparent before while being used. (If you’re wondering what Heidegger is doing here or want more context, check out my &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; posts). Most importantly, this new visibility changes how and what the thing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; - the implication being that situational contexts actually change &lt;em&gt;what things are&lt;/em&gt; for us (Dasein) in the world. So when my shoe ‘breaks,’ it changes how it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in the everyday-ness of my world. It stops being a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polyvore.com/cgi/img-thing?.out=jpg&amp;amp;size=l&amp;amp;tid=71957156&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoe&lt;/em&gt; shoe&lt;/a&gt; and starts being a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.celia-pardini.fr/_/rsrc/1316020452111/my-destroyed-shoes/destroyShoes3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;trash&lt;/em&gt; shoe&lt;/a&gt;. Its time is up. In his 1935 essay &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger-aesthetics/#HeiForArtIntThrPilHeiUndArt&quot;&gt;“The Origin of the Work of Art,”&lt;/a&gt; Heidegger himself actually looks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://harpers.org/wp-content/uploads/van-gogh-a-pair-of-shoes.jpg&quot;&gt;a famous pair of shoes&lt;/a&gt; as an example of how an artistic representation of them can pull together and have the power to &lt;em&gt;disclose&lt;/em&gt; a kind of life-world despite simply being ‘equipment.’ And it seems to me that a totally trashed pair of shoes does this very differently than a pair fresh out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wonder: when a thing’s lifespan as a thing is over (a lifespan determined in large part by its use context: i.e. a pair of boots that sits in a closet all year vs. pair used by a carpenter or roofer on worksites almost every day), what kind of lifespan does it acquire as something broken? How does the life of a &lt;em&gt;trash&lt;/em&gt; shoe different from a &lt;em&gt;shoe&lt;/em&gt; shoe, assuming that it’s possible these two shoes might &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; different things for me? An illustrative example would be something like comparing how we think of the ‘lifespan’ of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carsofamericainc.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/iStock_000013970322XSmall.jpg&quot;&gt;car battery&lt;/a&gt; with the ‘lifespan’ of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fullcarservice.org/images/category/carblog/carnews/bat_last/car-battery1.jpg&quot;&gt;dead car battery&lt;/a&gt;: the first has to do with human use, the possibility of travel, cold winter mornings, brand reliability, maintenance, usually a matter of years; the latter with molecular half-lives, recycling practices, landfills, all on a much longer scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sketch with the new pen, this of an abandoned vehicle, engine- and battery-less. With some color! (If you want to see the original I was trying to draw, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;http://i.ytimg.com/vi/j2SGlkFfH3Y/maxresdefault.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.23carintheweeds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Car in the Weeds&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a kind of mythical image for me. In his song &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomwaits.com/songs/song/368/Bad_As_Me/&quot;&gt;“Bad As Me”&lt;/a&gt; Tom Waits calls it simply “the car in the weeds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So two main questions: on the one hand, how do we conceive of time passing for things that are ‘invisible’ and ‘present-at-hand’ - things that are there in the background almost all the time, but that we take for granted until lost or broken? And on the other, how do we conceive of time passing for things that are out of sight &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; mind - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/06/26-trillion-pounds-of-garbage-where-does-the-worlds-trash-go/258234/&quot;&gt;things that have been cast aside&lt;/a&gt;, like this car is now, or my shoe soon will be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more: a pencil with a broken tip, and a pencil that has been sharpened way past its point of practical usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.23pencil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Broken Pencil&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;722&quot; /&gt;``&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when things break, when their ‘time is up,’ they acquire a certain kind of urgency. They come to the fore. It’s almost like they come back into existence from some kind of constantly humming background noise. All of the sudden you have to decide what to do with this thing - do you fix it? Replace it with something else? Replace it with a new version of itself? Leave it in the weeds (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Pacific_garbage_patch&quot;&gt;or the center of the Pacific&lt;/a&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions may feel simple, or perhaps too straightforward, but they are the kinds of questions that matter for Daisen (us, humans, beings for whom being is a question) when it comes to things in our world. And because they matter to us in this way, these questions matter for how these objects &lt;em&gt;are &lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;are not&lt;/em&gt; in our worlds - and by world I mean the highly contingent world with which a given person is familiar and in which they live their day-to-day lives, one that is changing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminds me of another scene from another 20th century novel, the “Time Passes” section of Virginia Woolf’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_the_Lighthouse&quot;&gt;To the Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (much of which you can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=ng0Tg0FhRggC&amp;amp;q=time+passes#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=time%20passes&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;here on Google Books&lt;/a&gt;). Describing a home left more-or-less uninhabited for years, she writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;So with the house empty and the doors locked and the mattresses rolled round, those stray airs, advance guards of great armies, blustered in, brushed bare boards, nibbled and fanned, met nothing in bedroom or drawing-room that wholly resisted them but only hangings that flapped, wood that creaked, the bare legs of tables, saucepans and china already furred, tarnished, cracked. What people had shed and left - a pair of shoes, a shooting cap, some faded skirts and coats in wardrobes - those alone kept the human shape and in the emptiness indicated how once they were filled and animated; how once hands were busy with hooks and buttons; how once the looking-glass had held a face; had held a world hollowed out in which a figure turned, a hand flashed, the door opened, in came children rushing and tumbling; and went out again. … Loveliness and stillness clasped hands in the bedroom, and among the shrouded jugs and sheeted chairs even the prying of the wind, and the soft nose of the clammy sea airs, rubbing, snuffing, iterating, and reiterating their questions - “Will you fade? Will you perish?” - scarcely disturbed the peace, the indifference, the air of pure integrity, as if the question they asked scarcely needed that they should answer: we remain.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think more on just how my busted shoe, the car in the weeds, and the too-short pencil go about ‘remaining’ in the world, and how this might differ from their still-in-use counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 13:47:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/10/21/inktober-10-21-when-things-break.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/13: Time Pieces and Graphs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-1013-time-pieces-and-graphs/&quot;&gt;on the Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello all - three more images for Inktober.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a continuation from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;my previous Inktober post&lt;/a&gt;, very simply, two tubes of toothpaste, both almost empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.13toothpaste.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Toothpaste&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was still thinking of the consumption of objects, for two reasons: first, because of their importance to a historical thinker deeply interested in time (and on my orals list), one Karl Marx, who writes on everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch10.htm&quot;&gt;the length of the working day&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch01.htm#S1&quot;&gt;labour-time itself here in the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And second, because a lot of people use toothpaste in their everyday life. It is something they consume very slowly, and often even forget that they have or that it’s running out; they measure out its consumption bit by bit over the course of many weeks, but its presence over time is ‘at hand,’ or taken for granted in a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start with Marx though, in the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt; (titled: Commodities) he defines the value of a commodity as “the labour time socially necessary for its production.” He then goes on to quote himself from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1844/manuscripts/preface.htm&quot;&gt;Economic &amp;amp; Philosophic Manuscripts of 1844&lt;/a&gt; saying that “As exchange values, all commodities are merely definite quantities of &lt;em&gt;congealed labour-time&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a phrase! &lt;em&gt;Congealed labour-time&lt;/em&gt;. As though the object in hand were physically made up of hours from the lives of others. The idea that an hour of life itself can be estranged from an individual and sold for monetary compensation, and that these hours of others then congeal into an object which sits on my bathroom sink for a set number of weeks is fascinating, and which Marx thinks through seriously, though too much to talk about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second point though, that people use toothpaste everyday, has to do with the thinking of another philosopher I’ve been reading while studying for my oral exams - &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/&quot;&gt;Martin Heidegger&lt;/a&gt;. Though he’s interested &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#BeiTim&quot;&gt;in his big work&lt;/a&gt; with ontological questions (like, what kind of being does the number 1 have vs. the color brown, a chair, the solar system, a historical event, my cat, etc) he also believes that things ‘are’ for humans (or &lt;em&gt;Dasein&lt;/em&gt; in his terminology, the being for whom being is an issue or question) in a way that is more natural. In his thinking, when I see a desk, I don’t go for some abstract, philosophical, Aristotelian route and think of it as a substance with attributes (such as squareness or brownness), I think more of whether or not it is the right size, or close enough to a reading light, or if it is an heirloom that needs to be treated carefully. That these considerations actually make up, in many ways, the ‘being’ of the table itself for Dasein (humans) was fascinating to me when I first started reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence: toothpaste! I brush my teeth twice a day and use toothpaste from a tube that looks like one of these. It is something that fits in my hand and I can tell how much time I have left with this particular tube just by picking it up. Using a brand new tube is very different from the ones I have drawn here, crumpling up tubes to try to make them last, to &lt;em&gt;extend their lives&lt;/em&gt;. The “time” of a tube of toothpaste, its lifespan, is relatively slow (or long) compared to, say, a quart of milk or loaf of bread. The same tube persists through many weeks of use, and there is even a certain feeling of ‘letting go’ and beginning again when I have to stop crushing up an old familiar tube and go buy new. And trying a new brand, flavor, or type of toothpaste is a strangely serious time commitment, a decision that persists in your everyday experience (and teeth) for weeks or months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connects with another picture, those of time pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.13laptopwatchphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Time Pieces&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to draw the things I look at during the day to tell what time it is. When this Dasein thinks of time (me), he probably thinks first of where he looks to ‘tell the time,’ the things I use to make sure that I am not late, or that I am getting enough sleep, or that I remember to eat lunch. For me these are my computer and my phone. My window into Greenwich Mean Time is almost always small numbers on a screen that sometimes fail to update to Daylight Savings. A lot of people have watches though, so I wanted to draw one of them too. I wonder how these objects of mediators of this standard time influence how time actually feels for the humans who use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is more abstract. I was thinking of Johanna Drucker’s work in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674724938&quot;&gt;Graphesis: Visual Forms of Knowledge Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and particularly an article she wrote for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/&quot;&gt;DHQ&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html&quot;&gt;“Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display”&lt;/a&gt; in which she gives some examples of how humanists can use graphical representations. So I decided to draw some graphs about how we might experience time in a 24-hour period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.13graphs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graphs&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was envisioning that a given person would travel along the path of the line, x-axis being each hour passing, and y-axis being… something else. Experience? Not sure - point being, although the same number of ‘hours’ passed for each line, the length, trajectory, and experience of each line (or sets of lines) was very unique. Would love to draw some more of these, or at least think through them a little more seriously before the month is out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 13:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/10/13/inktober-10-13-time-pieces-graphs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inktober 10/5: Three Sketches</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;my post on the Praxis page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/inktober-105-three-sketches/&quot;&gt;on the Scholars’ Lab.]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanted to put up a few time sketches for our own version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mrjakeparker.com/inktober&quot;&gt;Inktober&lt;/a&gt;. I’m aiming for every other day or so, so here’s three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three have to do with time and consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.5.movietime.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Popcorn&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love going to the movies, and usually opt for the biggest popcorn possible (bucket) but wonder how differently and quickly the ‘time of eating’ passes depending on how big your eating vessel is (I’m sure plenty of others have written about this - just Googling around quickly I found an entire website dedicated to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smallplatemovement.org/&quot;&gt;using smaller plates&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.5pintbythehour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pints&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one is another thing some people do to pass time together - having a drink at a bar or restaurant, which can go slow or fast. Here I tried to draw the rings that beer leaves behind as a marker of how much time passed where for the beer in this particular glass. Beer time! Reminds me of &lt;a href=&quot;http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Slughorn&#39;s_Hourglass&quot;&gt;Slughorn’s Hourglass&lt;/a&gt; in Harry Potter, which goes faster or slower depending on the quality of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.5cigarettebreak.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cigarettes&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is a cigarette - read a poem for orals by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/sherman-alexie&quot;&gt;Sherman Alexie &lt;/a&gt;with James Dean in it (called “Tourists”), got me thinking of the images of Dean &lt;a href=&quot;http://images.amcnetworks.com/blogs.amctv.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/2jacket.jpg&quot;&gt;with a cigarette in his red jacket&lt;/a&gt; (no color in that photo, but pretty sure that’s the jacket) and got thinking of how so many people frame “breaks” from their day, little slices of time, around something like cigarette “breaks.” As though they were carrying a pack of minutes in their pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 13:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/10/05/inktober-10-5-three-sketches.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time and Praxis 2015-2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Time is a massive concept. If you were asked to think about it – how it works, feels, changes, what it looks like, how people go about talking about it, or representing it – where would you start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a person interested and invested in critical theory, my initial reflex would be to go to philosophers, phenomenologists – writers like &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heidegger/#TemTem&quot;&gt;Martin Heidegger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/merleau-ponty/&quot;&gt;Maurice Merleau-Ponty&lt;/a&gt;, and so on. Or check in with narrative theorists, think again about what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%A9rard_Genette#Order&quot;&gt;Gérard Genette&lt;/a&gt; says about time and narrative in &lt;em&gt;Narrative Discourse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second reflex would be to look at art and cultural objects. I’ve been trying to watch and/or reconsider as many time-travel movies as I had time for, everything from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4CC60HJvZRE&quot;&gt;Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8wqVHjK2bQs&quot;&gt;Donnie Darko&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;to something more straightforward like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c4Jo8QoOTQ4&quot;&gt;The Terminator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes you find something unexpected – for example, trying to &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/657/&quot;&gt;untangle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Primer &lt;/em&gt;after watching it last week, Gillet (a fellow Praxis member) commented that manipulating time in films can have a certain scare-factor, almost like it’s a specific branch of horror movies. I’d never thought about it that way before. Time, and the manipulation of time, has the power to frighten us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, games: like &lt;a href=&quot;http://braid-game.com/&quot;&gt;Braid&lt;/a&gt;, where manipulating time is the only way to solve puzzles and progress through the narrative. Or (at Jeremy’s suggestion) checking out Ian Bogost’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://bogost.com/games/aslowyear/&quot;&gt;A Slow Year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, literature. I thought first to a classics like H.G. Wells’ 1895 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Time_Machine&quot;&gt;The Time Machine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;or Ray Bradbury’s 1952 short story &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Sound_of_Thunder&quot;&gt;“A Sound of Thunder,”&lt;/a&gt; where tourist big-game hunters go back in time to kill dinosaurs, but (spoilers) someone accidentally steps on a butterfly and changes the whole course of history. Then to Kurt Vonnegut’s 1969 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slaughterhouse-Five&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse Five &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(probably because it’s the first book I ever wrote a book report on), where a character becomes “unstuck in time” as he dips in and out of his life experiences. Or even to something like Ruth Ozeki’s 2013 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ruthozeki.com/writing-film/a-tale-for-the-time-being/&quot;&gt;A Tale for the Time Being&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(which I’m reading for my oral exams)&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;where relationships with past and present “time beings” might, in some ways, influence one another, even when those cross-temporal relationships are mediated textually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many movies, games, novels, short stories, poems, and plays I could go to here it’s nuts – not even looking at works with entangled narrative structures like the film &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0209144/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memento&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;or Faulkner’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Absalom,_Absalom!&quot;&gt;Absalom, Absalom!&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(for example). These above are just the first that come to mind, each of which interacts with time and experiences time a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first time writing here as a Praxis Fellow for the 2015-2016 year. Along with &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/charter-2015-2016/&quot;&gt;producing a charter&lt;/a&gt;, this year we’re all trying to think about &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; in as many different ways as possible, staying wide open with it and willing to explore any new possibilities, each coming at it from our own unique angle. Throughout the year, in our work and in posts like this, I’ll try to keep track of and share what I feel like I am able to bring to our work from my own unique perspective (apparently even if sometimes that means just talking about a bunch of time-travel stories I’m excited about). We’re only a few weeks in, and I can already say how excited I am to be working with the Praxis team and all the folks at the Scholars’ Lab this coming year. I can’t wait to see what we come up with!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/09/24/praxis_and_time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/09/24/praxis_and_time.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Physical Computing at DHSI 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/physical-computing-at-dhsi-2015/&quot;&gt;my post on the Scholars’ Lab site&lt;/a&gt;] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;In the beginning of June I had the pleasure of attending the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhsi.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Summer Institute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Victoria for the second year running. My experience this year was so good that I wanted to write a quick post sharing some of the highlights – so if you’re thinking of going to DHSI, are a regular interested in a class they’ve never taken, or have never heard of it and want to learn more, I hope this post sheds some light on the kinds of things people get up to at one of my favorite scholarly events of the year (and why I want to go again next summer)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;I spent my week in Victoria in a class called &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhsi.org/courses.php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;“Physical Computing and Desktop Fabrication,”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; taught by the folks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;UVic’s Maker Lab&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Nina Belojevic, Devon Elliot, Shaun Macpherson, and Jentery Sayers. If you’ve read any of my other posts or talked to me about the kind of stuff I do in the Makerspace here at UVA,&lt;span class=&quot;Apple-converted-space&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;I’ve taken a large number of cues from these folks in the past year as I’ve been learning more about critical making and physical computing. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;Meeting every day for five days in a row, the class covered a huge range of things that fall generally under the heading “physical computing,” which I think of broadly as just the interactions between computers and the physical world.&lt;span class=&quot;Apple-converted-space&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;We worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arduino.cc/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Arduinos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, wearables, a 3D printer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.makerbot.com/replicator2.html&quot;&gt;Replicator 2&lt;/a&gt;), a laser cutter (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epiloglaser.com/&quot;&gt;Epilog&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sketchup.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;SketchUp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agisoft.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;photogrammetry&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and more. If you are interested in exploring the full inventory of what’s available at the Maker Lab, you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/inventory/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;find that inventory here as a post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Hran2uky2vnXbjTfQ0RPsLhOmaVYKS2cY3X6Q9qMeSo/edit#gid=220944623&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;here as a spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. These technologies are capable of pretty amazing stuff - examples shared with us ranged from &lt;a href=&quot;http://technolojie.com/pu-gong-ying-tu-dandelion-painting/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;interactive paintings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BZysu9QcceM&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;wooden mirrors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.botanicalls.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;plants that tell you when they are thirsty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canassist.ca/EN/main/programs/video-gallery.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;technologies at CanAssist at UVic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; impacting the lives of those with disabilities.&lt;span class=&quot;Apple-converted-space&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;If you want to check out the whole week’s schedule for a more detailed account of what went on (along with more of the examples shared by our instructors) check out the index at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/uvicmakerlab/dhsi2015/blob/master/index.md&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;the class’s GitHub page&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;Along with trying out hardware, software, and discussing the larger implications of this kind of work, we also had a specific project for the week: to make a box. More specifically, our mission (quoted here from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/uvicmakerlab/dhsi2015/blob/master/index.md#theme-prototyping-a-box-material--metaphor&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;our class GitHub index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) was to “prototype your own box and explain how it operates both as a material and metaphor.” A deceptively simple task! But one that ended up producing awesome results - if you poke around on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/physcomp&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Twitter and #physcomp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/dhsi2015/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;some pictures Jentery posted from the class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you can see some of the amazing things others made over the course of the week.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;So what did I make? I called it… the gloom box.

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/07.6gloombox.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Gloom Box&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; /&gt;

So what is the box and what does it do? Like our prompt for the week, the gloom box is simple on the outside: it is a small box with a sad face looking helplessly at a button and an LCD screen. The LCD screen displays the words “BATTERY LIFE” with a large number underneath. When you push the button, the number under “BATTERY LIFE” decreases, and when it hits zero the whole thing turns off - that’s it. The gloom box has no other functions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;Before getting into why I made this thing (box as metaphor), a little more info on the thing itself (box as material).

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/07.6lasercutter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Laser Cutter&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;

The box was cut using an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epiloglaser.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Epilog laser cutter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from a large sheet of baltic birch. I made a simple frame design for the six sides of the box using &lt;a href=&quot;http://boxmaker.connectionlab.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;BoxMaker&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, then Nina and Shaun worked some magic to make it the correct dimensions for what I needed to put inside. The image on the top was something I made in a few seconds in Paint, then converted into a raster file that the laser cutter could read and engrave into the box.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;Like the outside of the box, the inside is also relatively simple:

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/07.6inside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inside Gloom Box&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;

An &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arduino.cc/en/Main/arduinoBoardUno&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Arduino Uno&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; hooked up behind the scenes via a breadboard and a bunch of jumper cables to the button, battery, breadboard, and LCD screen seen on the outside. To get the button to work, I ended up writing about thirty lines of code after borrowing from some examples in the Arduino library and other people working out similar problems online (and plenty of help from Devon!).&lt;span class=&quot;Apple-converted-space&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Unfortunately, the number underneath “BATTERY LIFE” didn’t actually correspond to the 9-volt’s battery - the code for that turned out to be too complicated. So I had it “simulate” the loss instead, setting “BATTERY LIFE” to a very high number and decreasing it by a random value from 1-9 every time the button was pushed. In what was described as a “delicious” twist of irony, when walking the gloom box over to share our work with other classes on Friday, the battery actually died before anyone had a chance to play with it. The line between “simulating” a battery’s energy expenditures and actually expending said energy can be very thin, apparently.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p3&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;That covers the box as material, but what about the box as metaphor? Why make a box whose only purpose is to inform you of how your interaction with it has depleted its battery life?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;My original goal had been to make a box that was “aware” at some level of some of the material costs of its own production, operation, or maintenance, ideally one that would highlight these costs in a way unique to the kinds of things physical computing lets you do. Two recent pieces of writing had me thinking this way: the first is an amazing post of Bethany’s from about a year ago titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;“Digital Humanities in the Anthropocene”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; the second was an article given as background reading for my DHSI class that I can’t find a link to online as it is still forthcoming, but can give the info for here: it’s called “Between Bits and Atoms: Physical Computing and Desktop Fabrication in the Humanities” and is written by Devon, Bethany, Jentery, and Kari Kraus and William J. Turkel in &lt;i&gt;The New Blackwell Companion to Digital Humanities. &lt;/i&gt;These two articles, coupled with some other reading going on around the same time (including Timothy Morton’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/hyperobjects&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hyperobjects&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;and N. Katherine Hayles’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/H/bo3769963.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;How We Became Posthuman&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), made the problem feel like an interesting one worth investigating.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;This small project turned out to be a great opportunity to explore certain problems I’ve been thinking about more generally. For example, the energy costs of “invisible” transactions that we make every day but don’t really see, like information moving from place to place, or from digital to analog - exchanges that feel like they aren’t physically embodied anywhere but actually are (a problem Hayles thinks through wonderfully in &lt;i&gt;How We Became Posthuman&lt;/i&gt;). Here I was thinking of the kinds of micro-expenditures that happen when we send a text, take a picture, or run some code. A box that made these “invisible” or “blackboxed” expenditures big, open, and obvious - even with something as basic as pushing a button - seemed like an interesting idea. Given the time frame I had to work on it, I ended up with something simple, a little silly, but also frustrating in potentially productive ways. A small gloomy energy puzzle, seemingly aware of its own helplessness in the face of its dilemma. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;It is reminiscent in simplicity and spirit of another example shared with us in class, &lt;a href=&quot;http://makezine.com/projects/the-most-useless-machine/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;the most useless machine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But perhaps more philosophically, it taps into questions of inevitability and the environment Roy Scranton asked in his 2013 NYT article, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/11/10/learning-how-to-die-in-the-anthropocene/?_r=0&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;“Learning How to Die in the Anthropocene”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where he takes a question like “How do we make meaningful choices in the shadow of our inevitable end?” and asks it on the scale of civilization itself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;So: is it a box-as-metaphor for planet Earth (no one person pushes the button enough for it to zero out, but enough people over enough time can make it happen – energy use understood collectively)? For the problem of energy in a more-or-less closed system (the only way to keep the box going is to introduce a new battery)?&lt;span class=&quot;Apple-converted-space&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;For existential gloom in general, applied not just to humans and societies but objects as well? I only had so much time to think the thing through, but thankfully I have the schematics and code and can remake it in our Makerspace if I want to keep tinkering around with it and the ideas that it – or projects like it – might represent.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;I hope this gives a window into some of the kinds of things people get into at DHSI. And I want to thank again all the folks at DHSI for making this amazing week possible, as well as my instructors and the other wonderful people in our class who made it such a welcoming and enlightening experience. Thanks for making a great space to tinker around in, and hopefully I will see you &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;next year&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/07/06/physical-computing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/07/06/physical-computing.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Printing Things That Print: A Miniature Hand-Press Project</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/experimental-humanities/printing-things-that-print-a-miniature-hand-press-project/&quot;&gt;my post on the Scholars’ Lab site&lt;/a&gt;] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few months, fellow English PhD candidate &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jpsa&quot;&gt;James Ascher&lt;/a&gt; and I have had a small side-project going on in the Makerspace: printing a small, desktop-sized hand press, and getting it to work consistently.  The model we found calls it a “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:113044&quot;&gt;Pocket Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt;,” but the idea of a small, hand-powered, personal “hobby” printing press is an historic one going back to Ben Lieberman and the “Liberty Press” – a history James will hopefully be posting about soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about our experience making this thing and trying to get it to work.  By putting it up here, I’m hoping it will be an example of the kinds of small exploratory projects that often become gateways into the growing scholarly field of remaking old technologies. On my end, I was also inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jenterysayers.com/&quot;&gt;Jentery Sayers&lt;/a&gt; in his recent visit to the Scholars’ Lab (all the way from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/&quot;&gt;Maker Lab at UVic&lt;/a&gt;) in which he discussed exactly this kind of project, though on a much larger and more rigorous scale (we have &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/podcasts/podcast-jentery-sayers-on-remaking-the-past/&quot;&gt;his talk in podcast form - check it out&lt;/a&gt;!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did we make? As linked above, we started by printing a desktop hand press. James then printed a plate with the motto, “Collaborate -&amp;gt; Iterate -&amp;gt; Discuss (and Print).” Using some ink we had meant for rubber stamps, we inked the plastic plate and gave it a shot – as you can see, what came out is readable (sort of) but not very pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/03.11press.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Press&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We jerry-rigged a few modifications (i.e. taped-on cardboard to raise and even out the paper) and then I printed out a single set of type from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:296026&quot;&gt;another model on Thingiverse&lt;/a&gt;, and sized it so that it would fit with our press. Printing with this type was a real pain as there was no way to keep them in place – a problem which, again, involved another series of jerry-rigged semi-solutions. Until we figured out a way to make this setting and pressing of type easier, our new press was going to be very limited in its applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/03.11type.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Type&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/03.11hijames.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hi James!&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, our goal in re-creation here wasn’t so much fidelity to a specific historical object as it was to explore the capabilities of an older technology (the hand-press) shrunk down in a new way to an individual desktop size that anyone could use on their own. Clearly, even this more modest goal led to a series of joyful problems.  It turns out stamp ink is, well, mainly meant for stamps, and that not all paper is created equal.  These may seem like obvious insights (and I’m sure they were to James, who knows much more about books as physical objects than I do) but for someone only recently beginning to learn about bibliography, textual studies, and the history of printing, these were practical concerns I had heard of but never had to really deal with before.  And they are all things we are still working on with making our press work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why does this matter? In an earlier post titled “&lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/remaking/&quot;&gt;The Relevance of Remaking&lt;/a&gt;,” Sayers offers some questions that I found to be helpful in making meaning out of experiences with old technology. Two in particular – “From what materials was it [the old technology] made?” and “Through what measures was it deemed a success?” – were particularly revealing in our case.  I was faced with problems like: what kind of paper works best when you are using plastic type? There’s a big difference between printer scrap paper we used originally and the softer paper, like from a cheap paperback, that we ultimately decided would work best.  For that matter, I wondered what kind of paper works best using &lt;em&gt;metal &lt;/em&gt;type – and what about differences in kinds of metals? What about different kinds of ink? What’s in “gel-based” stamp ink, anyways (as it reads on the back of the box)?  When we tried it again with a small sample of the oil-based kind of ink used in relief printing (courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.josefbeery.com/&quot;&gt;Josef Beery&lt;/a&gt;), and the prints came out much clearer, even after multiple presses (despite being limited by the granularity of the Replicator 2 model and print).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/03.11ink.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Press ink&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t new problems – they’ve been around for as long as people have been trying to print things. And despite being surrounded by scholars interested in these fields here at UVa, it’s been very easy for me to take them for granted on a day-to-day basis – something I didn’t realize until trying to deal with them first-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize: What James and I are up to here is very small-scale. But while piecing together something from a 3D printer is just the tip of the iceberg in terms of remaking old technologies, it’s been a really good way for me to get my foot in the door – although the technology we’re building is not strictly historical, the problems associated with it are historic ones.  Used in conjunction with the kinds of resources we have at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rarebookschool.org/&quot;&gt;Rare Book School&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://small.library.virginia.edu/&quot;&gt;Special Collections&lt;/a&gt;, this was a useful supplement to the study of books and book-making that I had the power to explore on my own. It certainly opened my eyes to a whole set of new questions in a physical, immediate way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the bigger picture: we haven’t thought through every potential use of this press, or what scholastic infrastructure it will fit into as a project.  In that sense it is surely subject to the “speculative condition” of purely exploratory research Bethany identifies and discusses in &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/speculative-computing/&quot;&gt;this enlightening post about speculative computing&lt;/a&gt;; but I would maybe liken our project even more to the kinds of projects she has &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;described in another post as “too small to fail.”&lt;/a&gt; In this sense, even if our press ended up being useless, this particular failure could serve as “a concrete experiment” our peers can talk to us about and learn from. But this smallness and speculative-ness have their payoffs – most of what I ended up learning about remaking old technologies I came across because we had already started working with the desktop hand press. It was only after diving in and having problems that I had the impetus to see what others in the Maker community had to say about similar projects.  What I found was really encouraging and left me with a whole bunch of new questions regarding our mini-project: when Sayers asks in another post, &lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/whyfab/&quot;&gt;“Why Fabricate?”&lt;/a&gt;, that we consider “for which methodologies and research areas does material depth especially matter,” and when Devon Elliott &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;ask in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cjc-online.ca/index.php/journal/article/view/2506&quot;&gt;“New Old Things”&lt;/a&gt; (an article cited in Sayers’ piece) for us to seek out “projects that allow us to imaginatively remake past technological artifacts and to experiment with past technological worlds,” the project acquired a new level of meaning for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if “make first, ask questions later” is a policy I would always encourage, but in this small-scale situation, given the time, resources, and encouragement to explore, following my interests ended up leading to not only to real, living problems, but also real opportunities to combine my work at the Makerspace with my work in literary study. Success!  In this instance, exploration resulted in the surprise of discovering a new set of important questions already being explored by others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/03/11/printing-things-that-print.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/03/11/printing-things-that-print.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting &#39;under the hood&#39; with Arduino</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/getting-under-the-hood-with-arduino/&quot;&gt;my post on the Scholars’ Lab site&lt;/a&gt;] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circuit boards, breadboards, digital inputs/output pins, analog outputs – “physical computing” can be an intimidating prospect for people with no experience.  As a person with almost no experience, I know these apprehensions first-hand.  Learning a new vocabulary, basic electronics, even basic programming? Ah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing from my own experience with Arduino to say this: getting started with physical computing and even basic programming is easier than it sounds.  Taking a page from the pedagogical playbook of &lt;a href=&quot;http://learncodethehardway.org/&quot;&gt;Learn Code The Hard Way&lt;/a&gt;, it worked best for me when I tried to &lt;em&gt;do &lt;/em&gt;something even if I didn’t understand everything when I got started.  I followed a set of instructions through to a given goal, and then learned about what I’d done and how I’d done it after the fact.  Arduino kits like the ones we have at the Makerspace are the perfect way to go about doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is an Arduino?  As &lt;a href=&quot;http://arduino.cc/en/Guide/Introduction&quot;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt; explains, these are miniature computers that “can sense and control more of the physical world than your desktop computer.”  They can take inputs from all sorts of sensors in the physical world and produce all sorts of outputs back into the physical world.  This ranges from making lights blink, a buzzer ring, taking temperatures, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://playground.arduino.cc/Projects/Ideas&quot;&gt;all sorts of crazy stuff&lt;/a&gt; that is much, much more complicated. And people are finding &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/Arduino-Projects/&quot;&gt;new things to make every day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I first got an Arduino it was just a box. Inside the box was an Arduino board, a breadboard, various wires and other things to plug in, and a USB to connect to my computer. Most importantly, there was an instruction manual.  Inside the manual I found a series of snappy pictures and diagrams with user-friendly (and often funny) explanations of what was going on.  I was using the manual from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sparkfun.com/products/retired/11576&quot;&gt;SparkFun Inventor’s Kit - V3&lt;/a&gt;. It suggested I get started trying to make an LED plugged into my breadboard blink at regular intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprise was this: going through this thing was not only not-scary, it was incredibly fun. It was like building from a Lego manual, but for a circuit board – the bright and strangely shaped objects fitting together, the clearly diagrammed instructions, and the tangible end-product that gives not only a satisfied feeling of having built something, but also the slight amazement at what has been built (I did that? – really?). My light was blinking in a matter of minutes. I disassembled and moved onto the next chapter, building a potentiometer (a dial instead of a switch) to change the rate at which an LED blinked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But where’s &lt;em&gt;the programming&lt;/em&gt;? Something has to be making all these electronics do what you want. Indeed, there is some programming in programs called &lt;em&gt;sketches&lt;/em&gt;.  But the programming was as simple as downloading the sketch files from the SparkFun tutorial into the Arduino program. Tada! Programming accomplished. And there are comments throughout the files explaining how the code works, and where you might try playing around with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so Arduinos are easy-to-use, inspire child-like joy a la Legos, and teach us some basics about physical computing and programming.  What about the bigger picture – why would I want to learn how to use them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I consider it a form of what Matt Ratto calls “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/01972243.2011.583819&quot;&gt;critical making&lt;/a&gt;,” something I talk about in &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/experimental-humanities/come-explore-the-makerspace/&quot;&gt;my first post&lt;/a&gt; here.  Second, it’s a portal into understanding some of the other amazing work digital scholars are doing with physical computing. I’m thinking of a recent article on “circuit bending” by Nina Belojevic on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nanocrit.com/issues/5/circuit-bending-videogame-consoles-form-applied-media-studies&quot;&gt;Circuit Bending Videogame Consoles as a Form of Applied Media Studies&lt;/a&gt;,” in which she takes apart an NES console, rebuilds it purposefully as a “glitch console,” and reflects on the social implications of her material engagement with the physical hardware.  “By actively taking apart, breaking, remaking, and tinkering with these material devices,” she says, “hobbyists, hackers, artists, and scholars can engage with, study, highlight, and challenge social justice issues” – encouraging people to ask not just about developers, but about “who soldered the VRAM onto their console’s circuit board.”  Jon Jonson at UVic’s Maker Lab has posted about a related project on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://maker.uvic.ca/snes/&quot;&gt;Building an SNES ‘Glitch Controller’&lt;/a&gt;” – work that, he writes, is “contingent upon haptic exploration and depends highly on trial and error,” a kind of creative play to which I think Arduinos can be a great introduction.  This is not to mention projects that use actual Arduino’s as an interface with the physical world, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/20-Unbelievable-Arduino-Projects/&quot;&gt;of which there are many&lt;/a&gt;. So come in and try them out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/01/19/under-the-hood-arduino.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/01/19/under-the-hood-arduino.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
